这世界改变了
The world is changed.
我从水中感觉到
I feel it in the water.
我从地上感觉到
I feel it in the earth.
我从空气中嗅到
I smell it in the air.
过去的一切
Much that once was…
都已失落
is lost.
现在没有人记得了
For none now live who remember it.
《指环王》
这一切都从铸造魔戒开始
It began with the forging of the Great Rings.
精灵族得到三只戒指
Three were given to the Elves:
他们长生不老，也是最有智慧、最公平的种族
Immortal, wisest and fairest of all beings.
矮人族分到七只戒指
Seven to the Dwarf-lords:
他们擅长挖掘矿坑，是山洞的巧心工匠
Great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
而人类
And nine…
则分到九只戒指
nine rings were gifted to the race of Men…
他们比别人更贪图权利
who, above all else, desire power.
（中土世界）
每只戒指都拥有统治各种族的意志与力量
For within these rings was bound the strength and will to govern each race.
但他们都受到欺骗
But they were all of them deceived.
因为另外还有一只被铸造了
For another ring was made.
（魔多）
在魔多末日火山的烈焰中
In the land of Mordor, in the fires of Mount Doom…
黑暗魔君索伦暗地里铸造了可以奴役世界的…
the Dark Lord Sauron forged in secret a Master Ring…
至尊魔戒
to control all others.
他在魔戒中注入他的邪恶、残酷
And into this Ring he poured his cruelty, his malice…
以及统治天下的可怕欲望
and his will to dominate all life.
一只驾驭一切的至尊魔戒
One Ring to rule them all.
一个接一个…
One by one…
中土世界的自由之士感受到至尊魔戒的力量
the Free Lands of Middle-earth fell to the power of the Ring.
但是有些人群起反抗
But there were some who resisted.
组成了精灵和人类的最后同盟，对抗魔多的邪恶兵团
A Last Alliance of Men and Elves marched against the armies of Mordor.
他们在险恶的末日火山为中土世界的自由奋战
And on the slopes of Mount Doom, they fought for the freedom of Middle-earth.
胜利终于在望
Victory was near.
但是至尊魔戒的力量
But the power of the Ring…
无人能敌
could not be undone.
就在这时候
It was in this moment…
大家都失去希望之际
when all hope had faded…
人皇之子埃西铎拾起他父亲的宝剑
that Isildur, son of the king, took up his father's sword.
黑暗魔君索伦，中土世界，自由之民死敌终于被击败
Sauron, the enemy of the Free Peoples of Middle-earth, was defeated.
至尊魔戒落入埃西铎手中
The Ring passed to Isildur…
他只有一次机会永恒地摧毁邪恶
who had this one chance to destroy evil forever.
但是人心…
But the hearts of Men…
很容易受到蛊惑
are easily corrupted.
而且魔戒有它自己的意志
And the Ring of Power has a will of its own.
它背叛了埃西铎…
It betrayed Isildur…
最后害死了他
to his death.
不该被遗忘的东西
And some things that should not have been forgotten…
也遗失了
were lost.
历史成为传说
History became legend…
传说成为神话
legend became myth.
两千五百年来
And for two and a half thousand years…
至尊魔戒的下落无人得知
the Ring passed out of all knowledge.
命运巧妙的安排
Until, when chance came…
让它蛊惑一个新的持有者
it ensnared a new bearer.
我的宝贝
My precious.
至尊魔戒落入咕鲁手中
The Ring came to the creature Gollum…
被他带到迷雾山脉的洞穴中
who took it deep into the tunnels of the Misty Mountains.
他的身心完全被魔戒占据
And there it consumed him.
终于来了
It came to me.
这是我的，我的爱，我一个人的
My own. My love. My own.
我的宝贝
My precious.
至尊魔戒让咕鲁得到违反自然的长寿
The Ring brought to Gollum unnatural long life.
五百年来它扭曲他的心智
For 500 years it poisoned his mind.
在咕鲁阴暗的洞穴中静静地等待
And in the gloom of Gollum's cave, it waited.
黑暗再度笼罩大地
Darkness crept back into the forests of the world.
在东方谣言四起
Rumor grew of a shadow in the East…
人们心中产生无言的恐惧
whispers of a nameless fear.
于是至尊魔戒知道
And the Ring of Power perceived…
它即将再度现身
its time had now come.
它舍弃了咕鲁
It abandoned Gollum.
但是出乎至尊魔戒的意料之外
But something happened then the Ring did not intend.
它被一个料想不到的人检到
It was picked up by the most unlikely creature imaginable.
这是什么？
What's this?
一个哈比人
A Hobbit.
夏尔的比尔博巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
一只戒指
A ring.
不见了！
Lost!
我的宝贝不见了！
My precious is lost!
不久的将来
For the time will soon come…
哈比人将决定世界的命运
when Hobbits will shape the fortunes of all.
夏尔开垦纪元…
The 22nd day of September…
1400年…
in the year 1400…
九月第二十二日
by Shire-reckoning.
袋底洞、袋射排、哈比屯、西区…
Bag End, Bagshot Row, Hobbiton, West farthing…
夏尔…
the Shire…
中土世界
Middle-earth.
第三纪元
The Third Age of this world.
《护戒使者》
“去而复返：
There and Back Again:
哈比人的故事
A Hobbit's Tale.
比尔博巴金斯著”
By Bilbo Baggins.
（去而复返：哈比人的故事 比尔博巴金斯著）
现在…
Now…
我该怎么说呢？
where to begin?
对了…
Ah, yes…
“关于…
"Concerning…
哈比人”
Hobbits."
（关于哈比人）
“千百年来，哈比人一直都定居在夏尔的…
Hobbits have been living and farming in the four Farthings of the Shire…
四个区域务农
for many hundreds of years…
完全无视于外界的存在
quite content to ignore and be ignored…
也满足于被外界忽视的状态
by the world of the Big Folk.
毕竟中土世界充满了数不清的奇异生物
Middle-earth being, after all, full of strange creatures beyond count…
哈比人一定显得不重要
Hobbits must seem of little importance…
因为我们既不是骁勇的战士
being neither renowned as great warriors…
也不被认为特别有智慧”
nor counted among the very wise.
佛罗多！有人在敲门，
Frodo! Someone at the door.
“事实上，有人曾经评论过…
In fact, it has been remarked by some…
哈比人唯一的狂热就是美食
that Hobbits' only real passion is for food.
这评论相当不公平
A rather unfair observation…
因为我们也对酿啤酒…
as we have also developed a keen interest in the brewing of ales…
和抽烟斗有浓厚的兴趣
and the smoking of pipe-weed.
但是我们一心所系的
But where our hearts truly lie…
是和平宁静
is in peace and quiet…
与肥沃的农耕地
and good, tilled earth.
所有的哈比人都热爱能够生长的东西
For all Hobbits share a love of things that grow.
无庸置疑的，我们的生活方式对其他人而言非常奇特
And, yes, no doubt to others, our ways seem quaint.
但是今天，特别是今天，我特别感受到…
But today of all days, it is brought home to me:
安享宁谧的生活其实很不赖”
It is no bad thing to celebrate a simple life.
（生日快乐 比尔博巴金斯）
佛罗多！有人在敲门，
Frodo, the door!
讨厌
Sticklebacks.
- 那孩子跑到哪里去了？ - 佛罗多！
- Where is that boy? - Frodo!
眼前道路无止尽
Down from the door where it began
蜿蜒崎岖又漫长
And I must follow if I can
虽然路程尚遥远
The road goes ever on and on
眼前道路无止尽
Down from the door where it began
虽然路程尚遥远
Now far ahead the road has gone
- 但我一定要继续前进 - 你迟到了
- And I must follow if I can - You're late.
巫师绝对不会迟到，佛罗多巴金斯
A wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins.
也不会早到，他一定准时照他想的时间到
Nor is he early. He arrives precisely when he means to.
见到你真好，甘道夫！
It's wonderful to see you, Gandalf!
我才不会错过你伯伯比尔博的生日
You didn't think I'd miss your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
那老不死还好吧？
How is the old rascal?
听说生日宴会非常盛大
I hear it's going to be a party of special magnificence.
你也知道比尔博，他把这儿搞得鸡飞狗跳
You know Bilbo. He's got the whole place in an uproar.
这样他应该高兴了
Well, that should please him.
夏尔有一半的人被邀请
Half the Shire's been invited.
其他的反正也会来
And the rest of them are turning up anyway.
夏尔的日子就这样继续下去…
And so life in the Shire goes on…
跟上个纪元没有什么不同
very much as it has this past Age…
充满了新加入和刚逝去的人，改变很缓慢的进行着
full of its own comings and goings, with change coming slowly.
如果有什么改变的话
If it comes at all.
夏尔的一切都制造得很坚固
For things are made to endure in the Shire…
用来一代传一代的
passing from one generation to the next.
巴金斯家族一直都住在…
There's always been a Baggins living here under the Hill…
袋底洞的山丘下
in Bag End.
也会永远住在那里
And there always will be.
说真的，比尔博最近怪怪的
To tell you the truth, Bilbo's been a bit odd lately.
我是说，比平常更怪
I mean, more than usual.
他常常把自己关在书房里
He's taken to locking himself in his study.
他花好几个小时研究那些旧地图，以为我没看到
He spends hours poring over old maps when he thinks I'm not looking.
跑到哪儿去了？
Where's it gone?
他好像在搞什么名堂
He's up to something.
- 好吧，你不说拉倒 - 什么？
- All right, then. Keep your secrets. - What?
但是我知道这一定跟你有关
But I know you have something to do with it.
我的天
Good gracious me.
在你出现前，巴金斯家族声誊一向都很好
Before you came along, we Bagginses were very well thought of.
的确
Indeed.
我们从不冒险或犯规
Never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
如果你指的是那次恶龙事件，那件事与我无关
If you're referring to the incident with the dragon, I was barely involved.
我只是推了你叔叔一把
All I did was give your uncle a little nudge out of the door.
不管怎样，你都正式被列为捣乱分子
Whatever you did, you've been officially labeled a disturber of the peace.
真的吗？
Oh, really?
甘道夫！甘道夫！
Gandalf! Gandalf!
烟火，甘道夫！
Fireworks, Gandalf!
- 甘道夫！ - 烟火，甘道夫！
- Gandalf! - Fireworks, Gandalf!
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
- 你回来了我好高兴 - 我也是，好孩子
- I'm glad you're back. - So am I, dear boy.
我也是
So am I.
（和宴会无关者不准进入）
不要，多谢了！
No, thank you!
我不欢迎访客、祝寿者或远亲！
We don't want any more visitors, well-wishers or distant relations!
如果是一个老朋友呢？
And what about very old friends?
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
- 比尔博巴金斯 - 亲爱的甘道夫！
- Bilbo Baggins. - My dear Gandalf!
见到你真好，111岁大寿！谁会相信呢？
Good to see you. 111 years old! Who would believe it?
你一点都没老
You haven't aged a day.
进来，进来吧！
Come on, come in!
欢迎欢迎
Welcome, welcome.
来吧
Oh, here we are.
喝杯茶？或是小酌两杯？
Tea? Or maybe something a little stronger?
我还有几瓶1296年的陈年好酒
I've got a few bottles of the Old Winyard left. 1296.
很好的年分，几乎跟我一样老
Very good year. Almost as old as I am.
我爸珍藏的，开一瓶如何？
It was laid down by my father. What say we open one, eh?
我喝茶就好，谢谢
Just tea, thank you.
你上礼拜就该到了
I was expecting you sometime last week.
其实也没关系，你一向都想来就来、说走就走
Not that it matters. You come and go as you please. Always have and always will.
只是我有点措手不及，家里只有冻鸡和腌黄瓜
You caught me a bit unprepared. We've only got cold chicken and a bit of pickle…
还有乳酪，不行，太寒酸了
There's some cheese here. No, that won't do.
我有覆盆子果酱、苹果馅饼
We've got raspberry jam, an apple tart…
但没什么可以当甜点的了，哦，不，我们没间题
But not much for afters. Oh, no, we're all right.
我找到一些海绵蛋糕
I've just found some sponge cake.
（孤山）
我可以煮几颗蛋…
I could make you some eggs if you'd…
跑到哪儿去了？
- 茶就行了，谢谢 - 好吧
- Just tea, thank you. - Oh, right.
- 介意我先吃吗？ - 你尽管吃吧
- You don't mind if I eat, do you? - No, not at all.
比尔博！比尔博巴金斯！
Bilbo! Bilbo Baggins!
说我不在家！
I'm not at home!
是塞克维尔巴金斯家的人
It's the Sackville-Bagginses.
- 我知道你在家！ - 他们想要这房子
- I know you're in there! - They're after the house.
我这么长毒，他们不肯放过我
They've never forgiven me for living this long.
我被这些烦人的亲戚
I've got to get away from these confounded relatives, hanging on the bell all day…
吵得一刻不得安宁
never giving me a moment's peace.
我好想再看到高耸的山脉，甘道夫！
I want to see mountains again. Mountains, Gandalf!
然后找一个安静的地方写书，啊，茶滚了
And then find somewhere quiet where I can finish my book. Oh, tea.
- 你真的要实现你的计划？ - 对，一切都在计划中
- So you mean to go through with your plan? - Yes, yes. It's all in hand.
我全都安排好了
All the arrangements are made.
谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
佛罗多起了疑心
Frodo suspects something.
当然了，他是巴金斯家的人
Of course he does. He's a Baggins…
不是硬瓶抱腹家的笨小孩
not some blockheaded Bracegirdle from Hardbottle.
你会告拆他吧？
You will tell him, won't you?
- 会啦 - 他很爱你
- Yes, yes. - He's very fond of you.
我知道
I know.
我开口的话他一定会跟我去
He'd probably come with me if I asked him.
但是我想，他还是衷心深爱夏尔的家园
I think in his heart, Frodo's still in love with the Shire.
绿油油的树林和草地
The woods, the fields.
潺潺的溪流
Little rivers.
我老了，甘道夫
I am old, Gandalf.
虽然我看起来并不老，但是我的心老了
I know I don't look it, but I'm beginning to feel it in my heart.
我的意志变得很薄弱
I feel thin.
一切都索然无味
Sort of stretched…
就像面包上的奶油涂得不够多
like butter scraped over too much bread.
我需要假期，一个很长的假期
I need a holiday. A very long holiday.
我并不打算回来
And I don't expect I shall return.
我打定主意不回来
In fact, I mean not to.
老托比种的，南区最好的烟草
Old Toby. The finest weed in the South farthing.
甘道夫老友…
Gandalf, my old friend…
这将是令人难忘的一晚
this will be a night to remember.
（生日快乐 比尔博巴金斯）
你好
Hello, hello.
小胖博哲，很高兴见到你，欢迎
Fatty Bolger. Lovely to see you. Welcome, welcome.
山姆，快去邀罗丝跳舞
Go on, Sam. Ask Rosie for a dance.
- 我想再喝一杯啤酒 - 不行啦
- I think I'll just have another ale. - Oh, no, you don't.
去呀
Go on!
我站在那儿
So there I was…
面对三个可怕的食人妖
at the mercy of three monstrous trolls.
她们争吵着…
And they were all arguing amongst themselves…
要怎么把我们煮来吃
about how they were going to cook us.
是一口就把我们给吞了，或是一个接着一个把我们压成酱
Whether it be turned on a spit, or to sit on us one by one, squash us into jelly.
他们喋喋不休吵个没完没了
They spent so much time arguing the whithertos and the whyfors…
结果天亮的第一道曙光
that the sun's first light crept over the top of the trees…
把她们都变成石头！
and turned them all to stone!
快点
Quickly.
上去了！
Up they go!
最大的那个啦！
No, the big one.
布雷斯格德尔太太，真高兴看到你，欢迎欢迎
Mrs. Bracegirdle, how nice to see you. Welcome, welcome.
这都是你的孩子？
Are all these children yours?
天啊，你还真是多产
Good gracious, you have been productive.
比尔博？
Bilbo?
塞克维尔巴金斯！
Sackville-Bagginses!
快，快躲起来！
Quickly, hide!
孩子，谢谢你
Thank you, my boy.
你是个好孩子，佛罗多
You're a good lad, Frodo.
你知道我是个自私的人
I'm very selfish, you know.
是的，我很自私
Yes, I am. Very selfish.
我不知道为什么你父母过世的时候要收养你…
I don't know why I took you in after your mother and father died…
但是我可不是想做善事
but it wasn't out of charity.
我想那是因为…
I think it was because…
在那么多亲戚当中…
of all my numerous relations…
你是巴金斯家族最有勇气的人
you were the one Baggins that showed real spirit.
比尔博，你刚跑到老爹酒店了吗？
Bilbo, have you been at the Gaffer's home brew?
没有
No.
好吧，我有，但那不是重点
Well, yes, but that's not the point.
重点是，佛罗多…
The point is, Frodo…
你会没事的
you'll be all right.
- 好了！ - 你要把它插在地上
- Done! - You're supposed to stick it in the ground.
- 插好了呀 - 插在外面啦！
- It is in the ground. - Outside!
都是你出的主意！
This was your idea.
比尔博
Bilbo.
比尔博，当心那只飞龙！
Bilbo, watch out for the dragon!
飞龙？说什么傻话，这儿有一千年没出现飞龙了
Nonsense. There hasn't been a dragon in these parts for a thousand years.
- 漂亮 - 再来一次
- That was good. - Let's get another one.
梅里亚达克烈酒鹿，皮瑞格林图克
Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took.
我就知道
I might've known.
致词，比尔博！
Speech, Bilbo!
致词！
Speech!
亲爱的巴金斯家和波芬家
My dear Bagginses and Boffins…
图克家和烈酒鹿家
Tooks and Brandybucks…
万庐伯家、丘伯家
Grubbs, Chubbs…
吹号者家
Hornblowers…
博哲家
Bolgers…
抱腹家
Bracegirdles…
- 和傲脚家 - 是傲足啦！
- and Proudfoots. - Proudfeet!
今天是我111岁生日！
Today is my 111th birthday!
生日快乐！
Happy birthday!
但是111年的时光太短了
But alas, eleventy-one years is far too short a time to live among…
我真想多跟你们在一起
such excellent and admirable Hobbits.
我只认识你们之中一小撮人
I don't know half of you half as well as I should like…
而我认识的人很少值得我喜欢的
and I like less than half of you half as well as you deserve.
我要做一件事
I have things to do.
这件事我拖了太久
I've put this off far too long.
很遣憾我要宣布宴会结束了
I regret to announce this is the end!
我要走了
I'm going now.
我要向大家道别
I bid you all a very fond farewell.
再见了
Goodbye.
你一定觉得这招很高明
I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
你没看到他们的表情吗，甘道夫？
Come on, Gandalf. Did you see their faces?
世上有很多神奇戒指，但是不该随便乱用
There are many magic rings in this world, and none of them should be used lightly.
我只是开个玩笑
It was just a bit of fun.
不过就像平时一样，你说的对
Oh, you're probably right, as usual.
- 你会照顾佛罗多吧？ - 当然会
- You will keep an eye on Frodo, won't you? - Two eyes.
我会尽力照顾他
As often as I can spare them.
- 我要把一切都留给他 - 那只戒指呢？
- I'm leaving everything to him. - What about this ring of yours?
- 那要留下来吗？ - 当然了
- Is that staying too? - Yes, yes.
我用信封装好放在壁炉上面
It's in an envelope over there on the mantelpiece.
不对，等一下
No. Wait, it's…
它在我的口袋
here in my pocket.
真奇怪，不是吗？
Isn't that… Isn't that odd, now?
是呀，有何不可呢？
Yet, after all, why not?
- 我何不留着呢？ - 你应该把戒指留下来
- Why shouldn't I keep it? - I think you should leave the ring behind.
有这么困难吗？
Is that so hard?
没有呀
Well, no.
当然有
And yes.
现在我突然不想把它给别人
Now it comes to it, I don't feel like parting with it.
它是我的，是我找到它的！它来到我身边！
It's mine. I found it! It came to me!
- 你也没必要动肝火吧 - 我会动肝火，全是你的错！
- There's no need to get angry. - Well, if I'm angry, it's your fault!
它是我的
It's mine.
我一个人的
My own.
- 我的宝贝 - 宝贝？
- My precious. - Precious?
以前也有别人这么叫过它
It's been called that before, but not by you.
这是我的戒指，与你无关！
What business is it of yours what I do with my own things?
那只戒指你留着够久了
I think you've had that ring quite long enough.
- 你只想独吞它！ - 比尔博巴金斯！
- You want it for yourself! - Bilbo Baggins!
别把我当成一个江湖术士
Do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks.
我不想抢你的东西
I am not trying to rob you.
我只想帮助你
I'm trying to help you.
我们都认识这么久了
All your long years, we've been friends.
请你像以前一样相信我
Trust me as you once did.
放手吧
Let it go.
你说的对
You're right, Gandalf.
戒指一定要留给佛罗多
The ring must go to Frodo.
天色晚了，路还很长
It's late. The road is long.
是时候了
Yes, it is time.
比尔博
Bilbo,
戒指还在你的口袋
the ring is still in your pocket.
我替我的书想到一个结尾
I've thought up an ending for my book:
“他从此过着快乐的生活，直到寿终正寝”
"And he lived happily ever after to the end of his days."
你一定会的，老友
And I'm sure you will, my dear friend.
再见了，甘道夫
Goodbye, Gandalf.
再见了，亲爱的比尔博
Goodbye, dear Bilbo.
虽然路程尚遥远
The road goes ever on and on
后会有期了
Until our next meeting.
它是我的，我一个人的
It's mine. My own.
我的宝贝
My precious.
黑暗中的谜语
Riddles in the dark.
比尔博！
Bilbo!
我的宝贝
My precious.
宝贝
Precious.
他走了，对吧？
He's gone, hasn't he?
他一直都说要离开这儿
He talked for so long about leaving…
没想到他真的走了
I didn't think he'd really do it.
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
比尔博的戒指
Bilbo's ring.
他去和精灵住在一起
He's gone to stay with the Elves.
他把袋底洞留给你了
He's left you Bag End.
还有他所有的财产
Along with all his possessions.
戒指是你的了
The ring is yours now.
- 把它藏起来 - 你要去哪儿？
- Put it somewhere out of sight. - Where are you going?
- 我一定要去办些事 - 什么事？
- There are some things that I must see to. - What things?
- 我有一些疑间一定要得到解答 - 你才刚到
- Questions. Questions that need answering. - You've only just arrived.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我也不明白
Neither do I.
要保密
Keep it secret.
把它藏起来
Keep it safe.
夏尔！
Shire!
巴金斯！
Baggins!
“第二纪元的3434年
"The year 3434 of the Second Age.
以下是刚铎之王埃西铎的记载…
Here follows the account of Isildur, High King of Gondor…
以及找到至尊魔戒的过程”
and the finding of the Ring of Power."
“我终于拿到手了
"It has come to me.
这只至尊魔戒将是我的镇国之宝
The One Ring. It shall be an heirloom of my kingdom.
我的后代将永远对它效忠
All those who follow in my bloodline shall be bound to its fate…
我绝不容许魔戒受到任何损伤
for I will risk no hurt to the Ring.
这是我的宝贝
It is precious to me…
我经过多少痛苦才得到它
though I buy it with great pain.
戒环的刻痕逐渐褪色
The markings upon the band begin to fade.
那些赤焰般的文字现在全部消失
The writing, which at first was as clear as red flame, has all but disappeared.
只有火焰能让秘密显现”
A secret now that only fire can tell."
夏尔
Shire.
巴金斯
Baggins.
巴金斯家族不住这里，他们都住在哈比屯
There's no Bagginses around here. They're all up in Hobbiton.
在那边
That way.
∮ 嘿呵，酒瓶我来了 ∮
∮ Hey, Bottle I'm here ∮
∮ 疗愈我的心，淹没我的愁 ∮
∮ To heal my heart and drown my woe ∮
∮ 下大雨刮大风 ∮
∮ Rain may fall and wind may blow ∮
∮ 路途仍然… ∮
∮ But there still be… ∮
∮ 千里迢迢 ∮
∮ Many miles to go ∮
∮ 雨声甜美 ∮
∮ Sweet is the sound of the pouring rain ∮
∮ 山丘流到平原的潺潺小溪也温柔 ∮
∮ And the stream that falls From hill to plain ∮
∮ 不过清亮过雨声或小溪的 ∮
∮ Better than rain or rippling brook ∮
∮ 是灌进图克肚里的啤酒 ∮
∮ Is a mug of beer inside this Took ∮
夏尔最近有很奇怪的人路过
There's been some strange folk crossing the Shire.
矮人族跟难看的他族人
Dwarves and others of a less than savory nature.
战争正在酝酿
War is brewing.
山上已经遍布了半兽人
The mountains are fair teeming with goblins.
那都只是传说与童话
Far-off tales and children's stories, that's all that is.
你说的话越来越像老比尔博巴金斯，他是个狂人
You're beginning to sound like that old Bilbo Baggins. Cracked, he was.
年轻的佛罗多大爷也要成为狂人了
Young Mr. Frodo here, he's cracking.
而且还很自豪
And proud of it.
- 干杯，老爹 - 干杯
- Cheers, Gaffer. - Cheers.
我们住的地方以外都不关我们的事
It's none of our concern what goes on beyond our borders.
不要去惹麻烦，麻烦就不会来惹你
Keep your nose out of trouble, and no trouble'll come to you.
- 大家晚安 - 晚安
- Good night, lads. - Good night.
晚安，金黄啤酒的甜蜜少女
Good night, sweet maiden of the golden ale.
小心你在跟谁甜言蜜捂
Mind who you're sweet-talking.
别担心，山姆，罗丝认得出谁是白痴
Don't worry, Sam. Rosie knows an idiot when she sees one.
真的吗？
Does she?
- 晚安，山姆 - 晚安，佛罗多大爷
- Good night, Sam. - Good night, Mister Frodo.
你有守密吗？它安全吗？
Is it secret? Is it safe?
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
把手伸出来，佛罗多
Hold out your hand, Frodo.
很凉了
It's quite cool.
你看到什么？
What can you see?
你能看到什么吗？
Can you see anything?
什么也没有
Nothing.
There's nothing.
等等
Wait.
上面有刻痕
There are markings.
好像是精灵文，我看不懂
It's some form of Elvish. I can't read it.
很少人看得懂
There are few who can.
这是魔多的古文字，我现在不可以念出来
The language is that of Mordor, which I will not utter here.
魔多
Mordor!
那说的是
In the common tongue, it says:
“至尊戒，驭众戒
"One Ring to rule them all…
至尊戒，寻众戒
One Ring to find them…
魔戒至尊引众戒
One Ring to bring them all…
禁锢众戒黑暗中”
and in the darkness bind them."
这只至尊魔戒
This is the One Ring…
是黑暗魔君索伦以末日火山的烈焰铸成
forged by the Dark Lord Sauron in the fires of Mount Doom.
埃西铎从索伦手中夺过来
Taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
比尔博找到它
Bilbo found it.
- 在咕鲁的洞穴中 - 是的
- In Gollum's cave. - Yes.
比尔博六十年来不动声色地持有至尊魔戒
For 60 years, the Ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping…
他因而延长了寿命，延迟了老化
prolonging his life, delaying old age.
但是状况已经改变了，邪恶在魔多蠢蠢欲动
But no longer, Frodo. Evil is stirring in Mordor.
至尊魔戒被唤醒了
The Ring has awoken.
它听到主人的召唤
It's heard its master's call.
但是他已经被消灭了，索伦已经被消灭了
But he was destroyed. Sauron was destroyed.
不，佛罗多
No, Frodo.
索伦的灵魂没有死
The spirit of Sauron endured.
他的生命和至尊魔戒紧紧相系，而至尊魔戒幸存
His life force is bound to the Ring, and the Ring survived.
黑暗魔君索伦回来了
Sauron has returned.
他的半兽人大军与日俱增
His Orcs have multiplied.
他在魔多也重建了要塞巴拉多
His fortress at Barad-dur is rebuilt in the land of Mordor.
索伦只需要这只戒指，就能让黑暗再度笼罩大地
Sauron needs only this Ring to cover all the lands in a second darkness.
他在搜寻至尊魔戒
He is seeking it.
全心全意、不择手段地搜寻
Seeking it. All his thought is bent on it.
同时至尊魔戒也渴望
For the Ring yearns above all else…
回到主人的手中
to return to the hand of its master.
他们本为一体
They are one…
至尊魔戒和黑暗魔君
the Ring and the Dark Lord.
佛罗多…
Frodo…
绝对不能让他找到至尊魔戒
he must never find it.
好
All right.
我们把它藏起来，从此再也不提
We put it away. We keep it hidden. We never speak of it again.
没人知道它在这儿，对不对？
No one knows it's here, do they?
对不对，甘道夫？
Do they, Gandalf?
还有一个人知道比尔博得到至尊魔戒
There is one other who knew that Bilbo had the Ring.
我到处在找咕鲁
I looked everywhere for the creature Gollum.
但是魔君先找到他了
But the enemy found him first.
他不晓得被拷打了多久
I don't know how long they tortured him.
但是在可怕的哀嚎和呻吟声中，他们听出两个名字
But amidst the endless screams and inane babble, they discerned two words:
夏尔！
Shire!
巴金斯！
Baggins!
夏尔
Shire.
巴金斯，他们会找到这里来！
Baggins. But that would lead them here!
什么人？
Who goes there?
你拿去，甘道夫！
Take it, Gandalf!
- 拿去！ - 不行，佛罗多
- Take it! - No, Frodo.
- 你一定要拿去！ - 你不能把魔戒给我！
- You must take it! - You cannot offer me this ring!
- 我要把它给你！ - 别引诱我，佛罗多！
- I'm giving it to you! - Don't tempt me, Frodo!
我不敢拿
I dare not take it.
更无法保护它
Not even to keep it safe.
你要了解，佛罗多…
Understand, Frodo…
我只希望利用至尊魔戒行善事
I would use this Ring from a desire to do good.
但是透过我，魔戒将释放无法想像的邪恶力量
But through me, it would wield a power too great and terrible to imagine.
- 这不能留在夏尔！ - 没错
- But it cannot stay in the Shire! - No.
的确不能
No, it can't.
我该怎么做？
What must I do?
- 你一定要赶快走 - 去哪里？我要去哪里？
- You must leave. And leave quickly. - Where? Where do I go?
离开这儿，赶到布理村
Get out of the Shire. Make for the village of Bree.
布理
Bree.
- 那你呢？ - 我会等你
- What about you? - I'll be waiting for you…
在跃马旅店
at the inn of the Prancing Pony.
- 魔戒在那儿安全吗？ - 我不知道，佛罗多
- And the Ring will be safe there? - I don't know, Frodo.
我无法回答你
I don't have any answers.
我必须去见巫师长，他有智慧与力量，相信我
I must see the head of my order. He is both wise and powerful. Trust me, Frodo.
他知道该怎么做
He'll know what to do.
你不能用巴金斯这名字
You'll have to leave the name of Baggins behind you.
这名字在夏尔之外不安全
That name is not safe outside the Shire.
白天赶路，别走大道
Travel only by day. And stay off the road.
我可以穿过农田
I can cut across country easily enough.
佛罗多，好孩子
My dear Frodo.
哈比人真不可思议
Hobbits really are amazing creatures.
只要一个月就能了解他们
You can learn all that there is to know about their ways in a month.
但一百年后…
And yet, after a hundred years…
他们仍然让你吃惊
they can still surprise you.
趴下来
Get down.
可恶的山姆卫斯詹吉！你一直在偷听吗？
Confound it all, Samwise Gamgee! Have you been eavesdropping?
我才没有偷听什么，我只是在窗外除草而已
I haven't been dropping no eaves. Honest. I was cutting the grass under the window.
现在除草未免太晚了
A little late for trimming the verge, don't you think?
- 我听到有人大声说话 - 你听到什么？快说！
- I heard raised voices. - What did you hear? Speak!
没什么啦
Nothing important.
我听到戒指、黑暗魔君和世界末日…
That is, I heard a good deal about a ring, a Dark Lord and the end of the world but…
甘道夫大爷，别伤害我，别把我变成死的东西
Please, Mr. Gandalf, sir, don't hurt me. Don't turn me into anything unnatural.
不要？
No?
也许不会
Perhaps not.
你有更好的用处
I've thought of a better use for you.
快点，山姆卫斯，跟上来
Come along, Samwise. Keep up.
你们千万要小心
Be careful, both of you.
魔君有很多眼线
The enemy has many spies in his service:
包话飞鸟野兽
Birds, beasts.
安全吗？
Is it safe?
千万别戴上
Never put it on…
黑暗魔君的爪牙会被那种力量吸引来
for the agents of the Dark Lord will be drawn to its power.
佛罗多，你要记住
Always remember, Frodo…
至尊魔戒想要回到主人手上
the Ring is trying to get back to its master.
它想要被找到
It wants to be found.
这就是了
This is it.
这是什么？
This is what?
我只要再跨一步
If I take one more step…
就是我离家最远的一次
it'll be the farthest away from home I've ever been.
走吧，山姆
Come on, Sam.
我记得比尔博老是说
Remember what Bilbo used to say:
- “旅行很危险，佛罗多” - “一旦你出了门…
- "It's a dangerous business, Frodo." - "Going out your door.
上了路，如果你不专心看路
You step onto the road, and if you don't keep your feet…
谁晓得你会被带到哪里去”
there's no knowing where you might be swept off to."
山姆
Sam.
木精灵
Wood-elves.
他们要去白色要塞外的港湾
They're going to the harbor beyond the White Towers.
要到灰港岸
To the Grey Havens.
他们要离开中土世界
They're leaving Middle-earth.
不再回来了
Never to return.
不知道为什么…
I don't know why…
这让我觉得悲伤
it makes me sad.
不管我躺在哪里，都有粗粗脏脏的根抵在我背上
Everywhere I lie there's a dirty great root sticking into my back.
闭上眼睛…
Just shut your eyes…
想像你回到自己的床上
and imagine you're back in your own bed…
上面有柔软的床垫跟舒适的羽毛枕头
with a soft mattress and a lovely feather pillow.
没有用，佛罗多大爷
It's not working, Mr. Frodo.
我没办法在野地睡觉
I'm never going to be able to sleep out here.
山姆，我也没办法
Me neither, Sam.
末日火山再度升起烟硝
Smoke rises from the Mountain of Doom.
时间不多了
The hour grows late.
灰袍巫师甘道夫赶到艾辛格
And Gandalf the Grey rides to Isengard…
寻求我的建议
seeking my counsel.
你就是为了这件事来找我？
For that is why you have come, is it not?
我的老友
My old friend.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
- 你很榷定吗？ - 千真万确
- You are sure of this? - Beyond any doubt.
至尊魔戒被发现了
So the Ring of Power has been found.
这么多年来一直在夏尔
All these long years, it was in the Shire.
- 就在我眼前 - 你却没有发现
- Under my very nose. - Yet you did not have the wit to see it.
你热爱的半身人烟草让你的思维呆滞
Your love of the halfling's leaf has clearly slowed your mind.
但是还来得及，还有时间对抗索伦的势力
But we still have time. Time enough to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
时间？
Time?
我们哪来的时间？
What time do you think we have?
索伦的力量几乎已经完全恢复
Sauron has regained much of his former strength.
虽然他尚未完全转生
He cannot yet take physical form…
但他的灵魂仍有强大魔力
but his spirit has lost none of its potency.
虽然被封在要塞中，但是他却无所不知
Concealed within his fortress, the Lord of Mordor sees all.
他的视线能穿透乌云、阴影、土地甚至肉体
His gaze pierces cloud, shadow, earth and flesh.
你知道我在说什么吗？
You know of what I speak, Gandalf.
一个被烈焰包围，没有眼皮的巨大眼睛
A Great Eye, lidless, wreathed in flame.
就是索伦之眼
The Eye of Sauron.
他正在聚集邪恶力量
He is gathering all evil to him.
很快地，他会召集足够的兵力
Very soon, he'll have summoned an army…
袭击中土世界
great enough for an assault upon Middle-earth.
你知道这些？
You know this?
怎么会？
How?
我亲眼看到
I have seen it.
真知晶球是个危险的工具，萨鲁曼
A palantir is a dangerous tool, Saruman.
为什么？
Why?
为什么要害怕使用？
Why should we fear to use it?
其他的真知之石下落不明
They are not all accounted for, the lost Seeing-stones.
我们不知道还有谁也在看
We do not know who else may be watching.
时间来不及了
The hour is later than you think.
索伦的行动已经展开
Sauron's forces are already moving.
那九个已经离开米那斯魔窟
The Nine have left Minas Morgul.
那九个？
The Nine?
他们在仲夏前夕跨越艾辛河
They crossed the River Isen on Midsummer's Eve…
伪装成黑骑士
disguised as riders in black.
- 他们已经到了夏尔？ - 他们会找到至尊魔戒
- They've reached the Shire? - They will find the Ring.
然后杀死它的持有者
And kill the one who carries it.
佛罗多
Frodo!
你不会真的以为哈比人能对抗索伦吧？
You did not seriously think that a Hobbit could contend with the will of Sauron?
谁都对抗不了他
There are none who can.
没有人能逆着…
Against the power of Mordor…
魔多的力量取得胜利
there can be no victory.
我们必须加入他们，甘道夫
We must join with him, Gandalf.
我们必须投靠索伦
We must join with Sauron.
这么做才聪明，朋友
It would be wise, my friend.
告拆我…
Tell me…
朋友…
friend…
智者萨鲁曼几时发疯了？
when did Saruman the Wise abandon reason for madness?
我给你机会
I gave you the chance…
自愿帮助我
of aiding me willingly…
但是你却宁愿选择受苦！
but you have elected the way of pain!
佛罗多大爷？
Mr. Frodo?
佛罗多？佛罗多！
Frodo? Frodo!
- 我以为我跟丢你了 - 你在说什么？
- I thought I'd lost you. - What are you talking about?
- 甘道夫跟我说过 - 他说什么？
- It's just something Gandalf said. - What did he say?
“紧跟着他，山姆卫斯詹吉”我会紧跟着你不放
"Don't you lose him, Samwise Gamgee." And I don't mean to.
我们还在夏尔，会有什么事？
Sam, we're still in the Shire. What could possibly happen?
佛罗多
Frodo.
- 梅里，是佛罗多巴金斯 - 哈嗓，佛罗多
- Merry, it's Frodo Baggins. - Hello, Frodo.
快起来
Get off him.
起来，佛罗多
Come on, Frodo.
这算什么？
What's the meaning of this?
你们偷摘老农夫马嘎的菜！
You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
快给我滚出来！
You get back here!
快滚，臭小子！
Get out of my field!
被我抓到，就要你们好看！
You'll know the devil if I catch up with you!
生什么气嘛，不过两根红萝萄
I don't know why he's so upset. It's only a couple of carrots.
还有几棵包心菜
And some cabbages.
和上礼拜偷的几袋马铃薯
And those three bags of potatoes that we lifted last week.
- 还有上上个礼拜的蘑菇 - 好了！皮聘，我是说…
- And then the mushrooms the week before. - Yes, Pippin. My point is…
他太小题大作了！
he's clearly overreacting.
快跑！
Run!
好险哦
Oh, that was close.
我好像摔断了什么
I think I've broken something.
烈酒鹿和图克家的人最会惹麻烦！
Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
什么？这是一条捷径耶
What? That was just a detour. A short cut.
- 去哪儿的捷径？ - 蘑菇！
- Short cut to what? - Mushrooms!
那是我的
That's mine.
好大一朵哦，梅里
That's nice, Merry.
这里也有，山姆
Here's a nice one, Sam.
我们最好躲起来
I think we should get off the road.
躲起来！
Get off the road!
快点！
Quick!
别出声！
Be quiet!
那是什么东东？
What was that?
你看到什么吗？
Anything?
什么也没有
Nothing.
这是怎么回事？
What is going on?
黑骑士在找什么东西或是什么人
That Black Rider was looking for something. Or someone.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
趴下来！
Get down!
我一定要离开夏尔
I have to leave the Shire.
我跟山姆要赶到布理
Sam and I must get to Bree.
没间题
Right.
巴寇伯理渡口，跟我来
Bucklebury Ferry. Follow me.
快跑！
Run!
这儿！跟上来！
This way! Follow me!
快跑！
Run!
山姆，快去松开绳子！
Get the rope, Sam!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
快跑，佛罗多！
Run, Frodo!
- 快跑！ - 快点！
- Go! - Hurry!
佛罗多，快跑！
Frodo, come on!
- 快点！快！ - 跳呀！
- Come on! Faster! - Jump!
- 最近的渡桥有多远？ - 烈酒桥，二十英里
- How far to the nearest crossing? - The Brandywine Bridge. 20 miles.
来吧
Come on.
- 你们要什么？ - 我们要去跃马旅店
- What do you want? - We're heading for the Prancing Pony.
哈比人，四个哈比人！
Hobbits. Four Hobbits!
而且老天，还离开你们夏尔，你们来布理有何贵干？
What's more, out of the Shire by your talk. What business brings you to Bree?
我们想投宿在旅店里，来干什么是我们的事
We wish to stay at the inn. Our business is our own.
好吧大爷，我不是故意找碴
All right, young sir. I meant no offense.
天黑后我就得多间一下
It's my job to ask questions after night fall.
听说附近有怪人游荡
There's talk of strange folk abroad.
小心一点比较好
Can't be too careful.
小心看路！注意脚步
Out of the way! Watch where you're walking.
（跃马旅店）
对不起
Excuse me.
晚安，贵客，需要什么服务吗？
Good evening, little masters. What can I do for you?
如果你们想歇一晚，我们有哈比人住的舒适房间
If you're seeking accommodation, we got some cozy Hobbit-sized rooms available.
我们永远都很乐意为小个儿们提供服务，怎么称呼？
Always proud to cater to the Little Folk, Mister?
山下，我叫山下
Underhill. My name's Underhill.
- 山下 - 我们是灰袍巫师甘道夫的朋友
- Underhill, yes. - We're friends of Gandalf the Grey.
- 你能告诉他我们来了吗？ - 甘道夫？
- Can you tell him we've arrived? - Gandalf?
甘道夫？
Gandalf.
喔，对了
Oh, yes…
我记得了，一个老头子
I remember. Elderly chap.
长长的灰胡子，尖尖的帽子
Big grey beard, pointy hat.
半年没见到他了
Not seen him for six months.
现在怎么办？
What do we do now?
山姆…
Sam…
他一定会来的
he'll be here. He'll come.
让开！
Get out of my way!
那是什么？
What's that?
朋友，这就是一品脱啤酒
This, my friend, is a pint.
有这么大杯的？
It comes in pints?
- 我也要一杯 - 你喝很多了！
- I'm getting one. - You got a whole half already!
我们来了之后，那个人一直看你
That fellow's done nothing but stare at you since we arrived.
对不起
Excuse me.
在角落的那位，他是谁？
That Man in the corner. Who is he?
他是一个游侠，很危险，成天在荒野游荡
He's one of them Rangers. They're dangerous folk, wandering the Wilds.
我不知道他的名字，但是这儿的人都叫他神行客
What his right name is, I've never heard, but around here he's known as Strider.
神行客
Strider.
巴金斯
Baggins.
巴金斯？我认识呀
Baggins? Sure, I know a Baggins.
他在那儿，佛罗多巴金斯
He's over there. Frodo Baggins.
我是他的表舅…
He's my second cousin, once removed on his mother's side…
也同时是他的表…
and my third cousin, twice removed…
- 皮聘！ - 稳住，佛罗多！
- Pippin! - Steady on, Frodo.
你躲不了的
You cannot hide.
我看得见你
I see you.
在处空中
There is no life…
没有生命
in the void.
只有…
Only…
死亡
death.
你太惹人注意了，山下大爷
You draw far too much attention to yourself, "Mr. Underhill."
你想怎么样？
What do you want?
要你小心点，你戴的不是小玩意儿
A little more caution from you. That is no trinket you carry.
- 我什么都没戴 - 是喔
- I carry nothing. - Indeed.
如果我想，我也能不被看到
I can avoid being seen if I wish…
但是完全隐形却不是件易事
but to disappear entirely, that is a rare gift.
- 你是什么人？ - 你害怕吗？
- Who are you? - Are you frightened?
害怕
Yes.
恐怕还不够怕，我知道谁在找你
Not nearly frightened enough. I know what hunts you.
放开他！否则我让你好看，长腿人！
Let him go! Or I'll have you, Longshanks.
小哈比人，你很有胆量，但是这救不了你
You have a stout heart, little Hobbit. But that will not save you.
你不能再等巫师了，佛罗多
You can no longer wait for the wizard, Frodo.
他们来了
They're coming.
他们是什么东西？
What are they?
他们曾经是人类
They were once Men.
人类伟大的国王
Great kings of Men.
但是骗子索伦给他们九只魔戒
Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them nine rings of power.
他们利欲熏心，毫不让疑地收下
Blinded by their greed, they took them without question.
结果一一沉沦于黑暗力量
One by one, falling into darkness.
成为黑暗魔君的奴隶
Now they are slaves to his will.
他们是戒灵
They are the Nazgul.
介于生与死之间
Ringwraiths. Neither living nor dead.
他们随时感受到…
At all times they feel…
魔戒的存在
the presence of the Ring…
被至尊魔戒吸引着，他们会一直追杀你
drawn to the power of the One. They will never stop hunting you.
- 你要带我们去哪儿？ - 荒野
- Where are you taking us? - Into the Wild.
你怎么知道神行客是甘道夫的朋友？
How do we know this Strider is a friend of Gandalf?
我想魔君的仆役看起来会更体面
I think a servant of the enemy would look fairer…
- 更令人厌恶 - 他够让人厌恶了
- and feel fouler. - He's foul enough.
没办法，只能相信他
We have no choice but to trust him.
- 他要带我们去哪里？ - 瑞文戴尔，詹吉大爷
- But where is he leading us? - To Rivendell, Master Gamgee.
- 精灵王爱隆的家 - 你们听到吗？瑞文戴尔
- To the house of Elrond. - Did you hear that? Rivendell.
我们要去见精灵
We're going to see the Elves.
- 各位，天黑才能歇脚 - 那早餐怎么办呢？
- Gentlemen, we do not stop till nightfall. - What about breakfast?
- 你们吃过了 - 才吃过一顿
- You've already had it. - We've had one, yes.
那第二顿早餐呢？
What about second breakfast?
皮聘，他不知道有第二顿早餐
Don't think he knows about second breakfast, Pip.
早午餐呢？午餐？下午茶？晚餐？宵夜？
What about elevenses? Luncheon? Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper?
- 他应该都知道吧？ - 我看不见得
- He knows about them, doesn't he? - I wouldn't count on it.
皮聘！
Pippin!
没有哈比人，她们吃什么？
What do they eat when they can't get Hobbit?
她是谁？
Who is she?
你所歌颂的女人
This woman you sing of.
是露西安小姐
'Tis the lady of Luthien.
嫁给凡人贝伦的精灵少女
The Elf-maiden who gave her love to Beren, a mortal.
她怎么了？
What happened to her?
她死了
She died.
睡一下吧，佛罗多
Get some sleep, Frodo.
艾辛格遵从您的命令
The power of Isengard is at your command…
地球君主索伦
Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
替我召集一支魔多大军
Build me an army worthy of Mordor.
主人，魔多有什么命令？魔眼有什么吩咐？
What orders from Mordor, my lord? What does the Eye command?
我们有很多事要做
We have work to do.
这些树非常坚韧，主人，树根很深
The trees are strong, my lord. Their roots go deep.
全都拉倒
Rip them all down.
这是风云顶缭望台
This was the great watchtower of Amon Sul.
今晚在这里过夜
We shall rest here tonight.
这些给你们，一定要随身佩带
These are for you. Keep them close.
我到处看一下
I'm going to have a look around.
别乱跑
Stay here.
我的蕃茄熟了
My tomato's burst.
给我一些培根好吗？
Could I have some bacon?
山姆，吃点蕃茄吧？
Want a tomato, Sam?
- 你们在干嘛？ - 煎蕃茄、香肠和培根
- What are you doing?! - Tomatoes, sausages, nice crispy bacon.
- 我替你留了一些，佛罗多大爷 - 笨蛋，快把火熄掉！
- We saved some for you, Mr. Frodo. - Put it out, you fools!
- 快熄掉！ - 这下可好了，蕃茄上都是灰烬！
- Put it out! - That's nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
快走！
Go!
退后，恶魔！
Back, you devils!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
哦，山姆
Oh, Sam.
神行客！
Strider!
- 快救救他，神行客 - 他被魔窟剑刺中
- Help him, Strider. - He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade.
我救不了他，精灵才有办法
This is beyond my skill to heal. He needs Elvish medicine.
快点！
Hurry!
离瑞文戴尔还有六天行程！他撑不下去的！
We're six days from Rivendell! He'll never make it!
你要撑下去，佛罗多
Hold on, Frodo.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
你看，佛罗多，是比尔博大爷的食人妖
Look, Frodo. It's Mr. Bilbo's trolls.
佛罗多大爷？他好冰冷
Mr. Frodo? He's going cold.
他会死吗？
Is he going to die?
他正在进入幽界，很快也会成为死灵
He's passing into the Shadow World. He'll soon become a Wraith like them.
- 他们就在附近 - 山姆，你知道阿夕拉斯草吗？
- They're close. - Sam, do you know the Athelas plant?
- 阿夕拉斯？ - 又叫王之剑
- Athelas? - Kingsfoil.
王之剑，那是一种草药
Kingsfoil, aye, it's a weed.
那能阻缓毒性发作，快去！
It may help to slow the poisoning. Hurry!
怎么了？游侠竟然毫无防备？
What's this? A Ranger caught off his guard?
佛罗多
Frodo.
[精灵语] 我是亚玟，我来帮助你
I am Arwen… I've come to help you.
[精灵语] 听到我的声音
Hear my voice…
就回到光亮
Come back to the light.
她是谁？
Who is she?
佛罗多
Frodo.
- 她是个精灵 - 他快失去意识了
- She's an Elf. - He's fading.
他撑不久的
He's not going to last.
一定要带他去找我父亲
We must get him to my father.
- 我找了你两天 - 你们要带他去哪儿？
- I've been looking for you for two days. - Where are you taking him?
五名戒灵跟着你，我不知道另外四个在哪里
There are five Wraiths behind you. Where the other four are, I do not know.
[精灵语] 陪着哈比人，我会来接你们
Stay with the Hobbits… I'll send horses for you.
[精灵语] 我骑得比较快，我来载他
I'm the faster rider… I'll take him.
[精灵语] 路上太危险了
The Road is too dangerous.
他们在说什么？
What are they saying?
[精灵语] 如果我能渡河
If I can get across the river…
我族人的力量就可以保护他
the power of my people will protect him.
我不怕他们
I do not fear them.
亚玟…
Arwen…
拼命骑，别回头
ride hard. Don't look back.
你在干嘛？戒灵还在追杀他！
What are you doing?! Those Wraiths are still out there!
把半身人交给我，女精灵
Give up the halfling, She-Elf.
如果你要他，尽管来呀
If you want him, come and claim him.
不，不
No. No!
佛罗多，别死
Frodo, no.
佛罗多，别放弃！
Frodo, don't give in.
现在不行
Not now.
请赐给我力量
What grace is given me…
让他度过灾厄
let it pass to him.
让他免于死亡
Let him be spared.
救他
Save him.
- 我在哪里？ - 你在爱隆王的皇宫
- Where am I? - You are in the house of Elrond.
如果你想知道，现在是10月24日早上10点
And it is 10:00 in the morning on October 24th, if you want to know.
- 甘道夫！ - 是的，我在这儿
- Gandalf! - Yes, I'm here.
你没有死算你幸运
And you're lucky to be here too.
再过几小时你就没救了
A few more hours and you would have been beyond our aid.
但是你的生命力真强，亲爱的哈比人
But you have some strength in you, my dear Hobbit.
发生什么事，甘道夫？
What happened, Gandalf?
- 你怎么没去找我们？ - 对不起，佛罗多
- Why didn't you meet us? - I am sorry, Frodo.
我有事耽搁了
I was delayed.
你不能随便和萨鲁曼绝交
A friendship with Saruman is not lightly thrown aside.
别再杭拒了，没有用的
One ill turn deserves another. It is over.
你不投靠魔戒
Embrace the power of the Ring…
就等着灭亡吧
or embrace your own destruction!
世上只有一个魔戒之王
There is only one Lord of the Ring.
只有他能够驾驭魔戒
Only one who can bend it to his will.
他不会和你分享权利
And he does not share power.
所以你选择了死亡
So you have chosen death.
甘道夫，怎么了？
Gandalf? What is it?
没事，佛罗多
Nothing, Frodo.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
- 山姆！ - 你终于醒了！
- Sam. - Bless you, you're awake!
山姆一直守在你身逢
Sam has hardly left your side.
我们好担心你，对吧，甘道夫？
We were that worried about you. Weren't we, Mr. Gandalf?
幸好有爱隆王，你开始痊愈了
By the skills of Lord Elrond, you're beginning to mend.
欢迎光临瑞文戴尔，佛罗多巴金斯
Welcome to Rivendell, Frodo Baggins.
- 比尔博！ - 佛罗多，好孩子
- Bilbo! - Hello, Frodo, my lad.
比尔博
Bilbo.
“去而复返：
"There and Back Again:
哈比人的故事，比尔博巴金斯著”
A Hobbit's Tale, by Bilbo Baggins."
- 太棒了 - 我想再回去
- This is wonderful. - I meant to go back…
在幽暗密林的小径上徜徉
wonder at the powers of Mirkwood…
探访长湖镇…
visit Lake-town…
再看一眼孤山
see the Lonely Mountain again.
但是我终于年老力衰了
But age, it seems, has finally caught up with me.
（夏尔）
我好想家
I miss the Shire.
我从小就幻想能到别的地方
I spent all my childhood pretending I was off somewhere else.
跟你一起去冒险
Off with you, on one of your adventures.
但是我自己的冒险却完全不同
But my own adventure turned out to be quite different.
我跟你不一样，比尔博
I'm not like you, Bilbo.
乖孩子
My dear boy.
- 我遗忘了什么？ - 这么快就打包？
- Now, what have I forgotten? - Packed already?
越早准备越好
No harm in being prepared.
- 我以为你想看精灵 - 是啊
- I thought you wanted to see the Elves. - I do.
- 你想看得不得了 - 是的
- More than anything. - I did.
只是…
It's just…
我们照甘道夫说的做了，不是吗？
We did what Gandalf wanted, didn't we?
我们把魔戒带到瑞文戴尔，我觉得…
We got the Ring this far, to Rivendell. And I thought…
你的伤快好了，我们也要走了
seeing as how you're on the mend, we'd be off soon.
回家了
Off home.
你说的对，山姆
You are right, Sam.
我们达成任务了
We did what we set out to do.
至尊魔戒在这儿很安全
The Ring will be safe in Rivendell.
我可以回家了
I am ready to go home.
他的力气恢复了
His strength returns.
但他的伤永远无法痊愈，一辈子都会跟着他
That wound will never fully heal. He will carry it the rest of his life.
这一路上…
And yet to have come so far still bearing the Ring…
这哈比人证明了他能抗拒魔戒的诱惑
the Hobbit has shown extraordinary resilience to its evil.
他不该扛下这份重担
It is a burden he should never have had to bear.
- 佛罗多已经尽力了 - 魔君正在蠢蠢欲动，甘道夫
- We can ask no more of Frodo. - Gandalf, the enemy is moving.
索伦的大军在东方集结，他的邪眼正盯着瑞文戴尔
Sauron's forces are massing in the East. His Eye is fixed on Rivendell.
你跟我说过，萨鲁曼已经背叛我们了
And Saruman, you tell me, has betrayed us.
我们的盟友越来越少
Our list of allies grows thin.
他的恶行不只如此
His treachery runs deeper than you know.
他以邪恶的技术把半兽人和妖精混在一起
By foul craft, Saruman has crossed Orcs with Goblin-men.
在艾辛格的洞窟培育一支军队
He's breeding an army in the caverns of Isengard.
一支能在白天行军千里的劲旅
An army that can move in sunlight and cover great distance at speed.
萨鲁曼要来抢夺至尊魔戒
Saruman is coming for the Ring.
精灵无法抵抗这股邪恶力量
This evil cannot be concealed by the power of the Elves.
我们无法同时对抗魔多和艾辛格！
We do not have the strength to fight both Mordor and Isengard!
甘道夫…
Gandalf…
至尊魔戒不能留在这儿
the Ring cannot stay here.
这危机是整个中土世界的事
This peril belongs to all Middle-earth.
他们必须决定如何结束
They must decide now how to end it.
精灵的时代过去了，迁移到别处
The time of the Elves is over. My people are leaving these shores.
我们走了你们要向谁求救？矮人族吗？
Who will you look to when we've gone? The Dwarves?
他们都躲在山洞挖宝藏，一点都不关心别人的问题
They hide in mountains seeking riches. They care not for the troubles of others.
我们要把希望放在人类身上
It is in Men that we must place our hope.
人类？
Men?
人类太脆弱了，他们没有希望了
Men are weak. The race of Men is failing.
努曼诺尔人的血液不再纯正
The blood of Numenor is all but spent,
他们的骄傲和荣耀早被遗忘
its pride and dignity forgotten.
魔戒会幸存，都是人类的关系
It is because of Men the Ring survives.
当时我也在场，甘道夫
I was there, Gandalf.
三千年前…
I was there 3000 years ago…
埃西铎取走至尊魔戒
when Isildur took the Ring.
人类屈服于诱惑的那天，我也在场
I was there the day the strength of Men failed.
埃西铎，快！跟我来
Isildur, hurry! Follow me.
我带埃西铎来到末日火山
I led Isildur into the heart of Mount Doom…
只有在那里才能摧毁至尊魔戒
where the Ring was forged, the one place it could be destroyed.
把它丢进烈焰中！
Cast it into the fire!
- 毁了它！ - 不
- Destroy it! - No.
埃西铎！
Isildur!
那天就该结束一切，但是邪恶却让它存活下去
It should have ended that day, but evil was allowed to endure.
埃西铎把至尊魔戒占为己有，皇室血脉就此断绝
Isildur kept the Ring. The line of kings is broken.
人类的世界早已失去力量
There's no strength left in the world of Men.
他们群龙无首，四处流窜
They're scattered, divided, leaderless.
还有一个人能让他们团结
There is one who could unite them.
还有一个人能继承刚铎王位
One who could reclaim the throne of Gondor.
但他早就放弃王位了
He turned from that path a long time ago.
他选择自我放逐
He has chosen exile.
你不是精灵
You are no Elf.
欢迎南方来的人类
Men of the South are welcome here.
- 你是谁？ - 我是灰袍巫师甘道夫的朋友
- Who are you? - I am a friend to Gandalf the Grey.
那我们为了共同的目的来到这里
Then we are here on common purpose…
朋友
friend.
纳希尔圣剑的碎片
The shards of Narsil.
这把利刀砍断索伦的手指
The blade that cut the Ring from Sauron's hand.
还是很说利
It's still sharp.
但现在只是残缺的传家宝
But no more than a broken heirloom.
你为什么害怕过去？
Why do you fear the past?
虽然你是埃西铎的后代，但并不是埃西铎本人
You are Isildur's heir, not Isildur himself.
你不会重蹈他的覆辙
You are not bound to his fate.
我跟他流着一样的血
The same blood flows in my veins.
一样的软弱
The same weakness.
你的时代即将来临
Your time will come.
你会面对同样的邪恶，然后打败它
You will face the same evil. And you will defeat it.
[精灵语] 邪恶的力量并没有征服我们
The Shadow does not hold sway yet.
至少你我还没被征服
Not over you… not over me.
[精灵语] 你记得我们第一次见面吗？
Do you remember when we first met?
[精灵语] 我以为我是走进了一个梦境
I thought I had strayed into a dream.
[精灵语] 过了这么多年
Long years have passed.
当初你没有现在的担忧
You did not have the cares you carry now.
[精灵语] 你还记得我当初说什么吗？
Do you remember what I told you?
你说你愿意嫁给我
You said you'd bind yourself to me…
放弃精灵长生不死的力量
forsaking the immortal life of your people.
我仍愿意这么做
And to that I hold.
我宁愿和你共度一生
I would rather share one lifetime with you…
也不愿意面对永生不死的孤寂
than face all the Ages of this world alone.
我选择成为凡人
I choose a mortal life.
- 你不能给我这个 - 这是我的选择
- You cannot give me this. - It is mine to give to whom I will…
像是我的心
like my heart.
来自远方的陌生人和老朋友
Strangers from distant lands, friends of old…
你们被召集来商量如何对抗魔多的威胁
you've been summoned here to answer the threat of Mordor.
中土世界正面临灭亡的命运，无人能幸免
Middle-earth stands upon the brink of destruction. None can escape it.
你们不图结一心就会遭到毁灭
You will unite, or you will fall.
所有的种族都无法幸免
Each race is bound to this fate, this one doom.
佛罗多，把魔戒拿来
Bring forth the Ring, Frodo.
果然是真的
So it is true.
在梦中
In a dream…
我看到东方的天空变暗
I saw the eastern sky grow dark…
但是西方仍有微光
but in the West a pale light lingered.
有个声音呼喊
A voice was crying:
“你的末日近了
"Your doom is near at hand.
埃西铎的祸害找到了”
Isildur's Bane is found."
埃西铎的祸害
Isildur's Bane.
波罗莫！
Boromir!
在伊姆拉崔，从未有人胆敢用那种语言吐出片语只字
Never before has any voice uttered the words of that tongue here in Imladris.
我不敢请您谅解，爱隆君主
I do not ask your pardon, Master Elrond…
我说了魔多的黑语
for the Black Speech of Mordor…
然而将来这可能…
may yet be heard…
在西方每一个角落都听得到！
in every corner of the West!
这魔戒是彻底的邪恶
The Ring is altogether evil.
这是一项礼物
It is a gift.
一个给魔多敌人的礼物
A gift to the foes of Mordor.
何不利用这只魔戒？
Why not use this Ring?
我父亲是刚铎的宰相
Long has my father, the Steward of Gondor…
他一直奋力和魔多抗争，我们流着鲜血
kept the forces of Mordor at bay. By the blood of our people…
保护你们的安全
are your lands kept safe.
把敌人的武器交给刚铎，让我们利用它来对抗邪恶
Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy. Let us use it against him.
你无法驾驭它，谁都不能
You cannot wield it. None of us can.
至尊魔戒的主人是索伦，没有第二个主人
The One Ring answers to Sauron alone. It has no other master.
区区一个游侠懂什么？
And what would a Ranger know of this matter?
他不只是普通的游侠
This is no mere Ranger.
他是亚拉冈，亚拉松之子
He is Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
你要对他效忠
You owe him your allegiance.
亚拉冈
Aragorn.
你是埃西铎的后代
This is Isildur's heir?
也是刚铎的王位继承人
And heir to the throne of Gondor.
[精灵语] 坐下来，勒苟拉斯
Sit down, Legolas.
刚铎没有国王
Gondor has no king.
刚铎也不需要国王
Gondor needs no king.
亚拉冈说的对，魔戒不能利用
Aragorn is right. We cannot use it.
你们只有一个选择
You have only one choice.
至尊魔戒一定要摧毁
The Ring must be destroyed.
那还等什么？
What are we waiting for?
金灵，葛罗音之子，在场的任何武器
The Ring cannot be destroyed, Gimli, son of Gloin…
都无法摧毁魔戒
by any craft that we here possess.
魔戒是末日火山的烈焰铸成
The Ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom.
也只有在那儿才能摧毁它
Only there can it be unmade.
一定要深入魔多
It must be taken deep into Mordor…
把魔戒丢到末日火山的烈焰中
and cast back into the fiery chasm from whence it came.
你们其中一个
One of you…
必须去做
must do this.
我们不能就这样闯进魔多
One does not simply walk into Mordor.
除了有半兽人看守黑色大门外
Its Black Gates are guarded by more than just Orcs.
还有永不松懈的邪恶力量
There is evil there that does not sleep.
索伦的邪眼更是虎视耽耽
The Great Eye is ever-watchful.
那是一片死寂的荒原
It is a barren wasteland…
布满烈焰、灰烬和尘埃
riddled with fire, and ash and dust.
光是空中就充满致命毒气
The very air you breathe is a poisonous fume.
就算有千军万马也办不到，这真荒唐
Not with 10, 000 men could you do this. It is folly.
你没有听到爱隆王说的话吗？魔戒一定要毁灭掉
Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said? The Ring must be destroyed.
那你认为该由你来完成啰！
And I suppose you think you are the one to do it!
如果失败了，魔戒被索伦抢回去怎么办？
And if we fail, what then? What happens when Sauron takes back what is his?
我绝不容许魔戒落入精灵手中！
I will be dead before I see the Ring in the hands of an Elf!
精灵都不可靠！
Never trust an Elf!
你们不懂吗？
Do you not understand?
我们在这里吵嘴的时候，索伦的力量正在增强！
While you bicker amongst yourselves, Sauron's power grows!
没有人躲得过！每个人都会遭到毁灭！
None can escape it! You'll all be destroyed!
我愿意
I will take it.
我愿意把魔戒带到魔多
I will take the Ring to Mordor.
虽然…
Though…
我不认得路
I do not know the way.
我愿意协助你，佛罗多巴金斯
I will help you bear this burden, Frodo Baggins…
只要你愿背负重担
as long as it is yours to bear.
我愿意牺牲性命保护你的安危
If by my life or death I can protect you…
我愿意
I will.
我的剑会保护你
You have my sword.
还有我的弓箭
And you have my bow.
以及我的斧头
And my axe.
你背负着大家的命运，小子
You carry the fates of us all, little one.
如果这是大家的决定…
If this is indeed the will of the Council…
刚铎也会支持
then Gondor will see it done.
佛罗多大爷到哪儿我都要跟去
Frodo's not going anywhere without me.
没错，是很难拆散你们
It is hardly possible to separate you…
连你没份参加的秘密会议，你都来了
even when he is summoned to a secret Council and you are not.
我们也要跟去！
We're coming too!
除非你把我们五花大绑送回家
You'll have to send us home tied up in a sack to stop us.
反正你需要聪明人来完成这…
Anyway, you need people of intelligence on this sort of…
任务
mission.
探索
Quest.
东西
Thing.
你第一个就不合格，皮聘
Well, that rules you out, Pip.
九名同伴
Nine companions.
就这样吧
So be it.
你们是魔戒远征队
You shall be the Fellowship of the Ring.
好极了！
Great!
我们要去哪儿？
Where are we going?
她想保护她的孩子…
She wanted to protect her child…
她以为你在瑞文戴尔会很安全
she thought in Rivendell you would be safe.
你的母亲内心深处明白，你一辈子都躲不过纠缠
In her heart, your mother knew you'd be hunted all your life.
你逃脱不了你的命运
That you'd never escape your fate.
精灵的技术能够重新铸造人皇的剑
The skill of the Elves can reforge the sword of kings…
但是只有你有力量能够运用
but only you have the power to wield it.
我不想要那个力量
I do not want that power.
我一直都不想要
I have never wanted it.
你是皇家血脉最后的传人，无人能代替
You are the last of that bloodline. There is no other.
我的老剑，刺针
My old sword! Sting.
来，拿去
Here, take it. Take it.
- 好轻哦 - 没错，精灵铸的
- It's so light. - Yes. Made by the Elves, you know.
半兽人接近，剑身就会发亮
The blade glows blue when Orcs are close.
这样一来你就知道要格外小心
And it's times like that, my lad, when you have to be extra careful.
这玩意儿更棒
Here's a pretty thing.
秘银
Mithril.
轻若鸿毛、韧如龙麟
As light as a feather, and as hard as dragon scales.
让我看着你穿上，快点
Let me see you put it on. Come on.
我的老戒指
My old ring.
我真的很想…
I should very much like…
再把它握在手中
to hold it again, one last time.
我很抱歉把你卷进这件事，孩子
I'm sorry I brought this upon you, my boy.
很抱歉让你扛这重担
I'm sorry that you must carry this burden.
我对这一切都感到很抱歉
I'm sorry for everything.
持戒者准备出发到末日火山
The Ring-bearer is setting out on the Quest of Mount Doom.
与他一起旅行的各位不受任何誓言…
On you who travel with him, no oath…
任何承诺约束，随时可以中断旅程
nor bond is laid to go further than you will.
再会了，坚持你们的目的
Farewell. Hold to your purpose.
愿全体精灵与人类…
May the blessings of Elves and Men…
与自由之民的祝福跟随着你们
and all Free Folk go with you.
远征队等待持戒者启程
The Fellowship awaits the Ring-bearer.
甘道夫，魔多是往左还是往右？
Mordor, Gandalf, is it left or right?
往左
Left.
我们向迷雾山脉以西走四十天
We must hold to this course, west of the Misty Mountains, for 40 days.
幸运的话就能赶到洛汗隘口
If our luck holds, the Gap of Rohan will still be open to us.
从那儿往东走到魔多
From there, our road turns east to Mordor.
二，一，五，好！非常好
Two, one, five. Good! Very good.
脚步要快
Move your feet.
- 你好帅哦，皮聘 - 谢谢
- You look good, Pippin. - Thanks.
快一点！
Faster!
虽然你们都不问我的意见
If anyone was to ask for my opinion, which I note they're not…
我还是要说我们在绕远路
I'd say we were taking the long way 'round.
甘道夫，我们可以穿过摩瑞亚矿坑
Gandalf, we could pass through the Mines of Moria.
我表哥巴林会以皇家礼节热烈欢迎我们
My cousin Balin would give us a royal welcome.
不行，金灵，别无选择才能走摩瑞亚矿坑
No, I would not take the road through Moria unless I had no other choice.
对不起！
Sorry!
捉住他！
Get him!
- 夏尔万岁！ - 把他压住，梅里！
- For the Shire! - Hold him. Hold him down, Merry!
各位，够了
Gentlemen, that's enough.
你抓住我了！你抓住我了！
You've got my arm! You've got my arm!
- 那是什么？ - 没什么，只是一朵乌云
- What is that? - Nothing. It's just a wisp of cloud.
迎着风…
It's moving fast.
却移动得很快
Against the wind.
- 登兰德的乌鸦！ - 快躲起来！
- Crebain from Dunland! - Hide!
- 快点！ - 躲起来！
- Hurry! - Take cover!
萨鲁曼的眼线
Spies of Saruman.
南方的路受到监视
The passage south is being watched.
我们一定要攀越卡兰拉斯山
We must take the Pass of Caradhras.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
波罗莫
Boromir.
我们受尽了恐惧和疑虑的折磨
It is a strange fate that we should suffer so much fear and doubt…
就为了这小玩意儿
over so small a thing.
这小小的玩意儿
Such a little thing.
波罗莫！
Boromir!
把魔戒还给佛罗多
Give the Ring to Frodo.
遵命
As you wish.
我才不要它
I care not.
甘道夫，你想带领他们越过卡兰拉斯山
So, Gandalf, you try to lead them over Caradhras.
要是失败，你要到哪儿去？
And if that fails, where then will you go?
要是你被高山峻岭打败
If the mountain defeats you…
你肯冒更大的危险吗？
will you risk a more dangerous road?
空气中有可怕的声音
There is a fell voice on the air.
那是萨鲁曼！
It's Saruman!
他想造成山崩！我们一定要回头，甘道夫！
He's trying to bring down the mountain! Gandalf, we must turn back!
不行！
No!
我们一定要离开山顶！
We must get off the mountain!
赶到洛汗隘口，走西路到我的城市！
Make for the Gap of Rohan, and take the west road to my city!
洛汗隘口离艾辛格太近了！
The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to Isengard!
上面走不成就走下面吧
We cannot pass over a mountain. Let us go under it.
让我们穿过摩瑞亚矿坑
Let us go through the Mines of Moria.
摩瑞亚，你很怕穿过矿坑
Moria. You fear to go into those mines.
矮人太贪心，挖得太深
The Dwarves delved too greedily and too deep.
你知道他们在凯撒督姆的黑暗中唤醒了
You know what they awoke in the darkness of Khazad-dum:
邪恶的炎魔
Shadow and flame.
让魔戒持有者决定
Let the Ring-bearer decide.
我们不能在这里逗留！
We cannot stay here!
哈比人会葬身于此！
This will be the death of the Hobbits.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
我们穿过矿坑吧
We will go through the mines.
就这样吧
So be it.
佛罗多，过来帮个老人吧
Frodo, come and help an old man.
你的肩膀还好吗？
How is your shoulder?
- 比之前好多了 - 魔戒呢？
- Better than it was. - And the Ring?
你感觉到那股力量越来越强大了，对不对？
You feel its power growing, don't you?
我也感觉到了，你一定要小心
I've felt it too. You must be careful now.
远征队之外的邪恶会被召唤而来
Evil will be drawn to you from outside the Fellowship.
远征队之内的，恐怕也会
And, I fear, from within.
- 我能相信谁呢？ - 你一定要相信你自己
- Who then do I trust? - You must trust yourself.
相信你本身的力量
Trust your own strengths.
- 什么意思？ - 这世界有许多不同的力量
- What do you mean? - There are many powers in this world…
有善有恶
for good or for evil.
有些力量比我进强大
Some are greater than I am.
有些我也还没测试过
And against some I have not yet been tested.
摩瑞亚矿坑…
The walls…
之墙
of Moria.
矮人大门关闭的时候是隐形的
Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
对，精灵，如果忘记秘密了，连主人自己都找不到
Yes, Gimli, their own masters cannot find them if their secrets are forgotten.
我为什么不觉得意外？
Why doesn't that surprise me?
让我看看
Well, let's see.
伊希尔丁金屑
Ithildin.
这只会反射星光和月光
It mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
上面窝着：“都灵之门、摩瑞亚之主
It reads, "The Doors of Durin, Lord of Moria.
- 开口说，朋友，然后进入” - 那是什么意思？
- Speak, friend, and enter." - What do you suppose that means?
很简单，如果是朋友，说出暗语门就开了
It's simple. If you are a friend, you speak the password and the doors will open.
没有动静
Nothing's happening.
我曾经很熟悉精灵人类和半兽人…
I once knew every spell in all the tongues of Elves…
所有语言中的咒捂
Men and Orcs.
现在你要怎么办？
What are you going to do, then?
用你的头撞门，，皮瑞格林图克！
Knock your head against these doors, Peregrin Took!
如果那还不够撞碎这扇门…
And if that does not shatter them…
那就不要用蠢问题干扰我
and I am allowed a little peace from foolish questions…
我会尽量想出暗语
I will try to find the opening words.
马儿不能进入矿坑
Mines are no place for a pony.
- 就算像比尔一样勇敢也不行 - 再见了，比尔
- Even one so brave as Bill. - Bye-bye, Bill.
去吧，比尔
Go on, Bill. Go on.
放心，她知道路回家
Don't worry, Sam, he knows the way home.
别玩水
Do not disturb the water.
啊，没用了
Oh, it's useless.
这是一个谜语
It's a riddle.
开口说“朋友”，然后进入
"Speak friend and enter."
朋友的精灵话怎么说？
What's the Elvish word for "friend"?
[精灵语] 朋友
Mellon.
你很快就会见识到矮人族著名的热情
Soon, Master Elf, you will enjoy the fabled hospitality of the Dwarves.
熊熊的火焰、清谅的啤酒，有大块的烤肉吃！
Roaring fires, malt beer, ripe meat off the bone!
这就是我表哥巴林的家
This, my friend, is the home of my cousin Balin.
就是他们所渭的矿坑
And they call it a mine.
矿坑！
A mine!
这不是矿坑，这是坟墓
This is no mine. It's a tomb.
不！
No…
No!
半兽人
Goblins.
我们应该去洛汗隘口，不该来这儿的
We make for the Gap of Rohan. We should never have come here.
快走！快呀！
Now, get out of here. Get out!
- 佛罗多！ - 救我！
- Frodo! - Help!
神行客！
Strider!
- 救我！ - 在这儿！
- Help! - Get off him!
亚拉冈！
Aragorn!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
快进去矿坑！
Into the mines!
- 勒苟拉斯！ - 快进去！
- Legolas! - Into the cave!
快跑！
Run!
现在只剩下一个选择
We now have but one choice.
我们一定要穿过黑暗的摩瑞亚矿坑
We must face the long dark of Moria.
大家要提高警觉
Be on your guard.
在这个黑暗的地底世界
There are older and fouler things than Orcs…
有比半兽人更可怕的怪物
in the deep places of the world.
安静，要走四天才能到另一边
Quietly now. It's a four-day journey to the other side.
希望我们不会惊动什么
Let us hope that our presence may go unnoticed.
摩瑞亚的财富不在于金矿
The wealth of Moria was not in gold…
或珠宝…
or jewels…
而是秘银
but mithril.
比尔博有一件秘银圈罩衫，是索林给他的
Bilbo had a shirt of mithril rings that Thorin gave him.
- 值得献给人皇的礼物 - 是的
- Oh, that was a kingly gift. - Yes.
我从来没跟他说过
I never told him…
那件罩衫比整座夏尔更值钱
but its worth was greater than the value of the Shire.
皮聘
Pippin.
我不记得这地方
I have no memory of this place.
- 我们迷路了吗？ - 不是
- Are we lost? - No.
- 应该迷路了 - 甘道夫正在想
- I think we are. - Gandalf's thinking.
- 梅里？ - 干嘛？
- Merry? - What?
我饿了
I'm hungry.
- 下面有动静 - 那是咕鲁
- There's something down there. - It's Gollum.
- 咕鲁 - 他跟了我们三天
- Gollum? - He's been following us for three days.
- 他从巴拉多的地牢逃出来？ - 逃出…
- He escaped the dungeons of Barad-dur? - Escaped…
是被放出来吧
or was set loose.
现在魔戒带他来到这儿
Now the Ring has brought him here.
他永远渴望拥有魔戒
He will never be rid of his need for it.
他对魔戒又爱又恨，就像他对自己爱恨交加
He hates and loves the Ring, as he hates and loves himself.
史麦戈的一生是很悲惨的故事
Smeagol's life is a sad story.
是的，魔戒找到他之前，他叫史麦戈
Yes, Smeagol he was once called. Before the Ring found him.
在魔戒让他发狂之前
Before it drove him mad.
可惜比尔博当时有机会，却没杀了他
It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him when he had the chance.
可惜？
Pity?
比尔博是可怜他才没杀他
It is pity that stayed Bilbo's hand.
有很多活人本来就该死，也有些死人本来命不该绝
Many that live deserve death. Some that die deserve life.
你能这样断定吗，佛罗多？
Can you give it to them, Frodo?
千万别轻易断定别人的生死
Do not be too eager to deal out death and judgment.
就远智者都无法决定命运
Even the very wise cannot see all ends.
我直觉地认为不管是好是坏，咕鲁都会跟这趟探险有关
My heart tells me that Gollum has some part to play yet, for good or ill…
在这一切结束前
before this is over.
比尔博一时心软影响了很多人
The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
我真希望魔戒没在我手中
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
真希望这一切都没发生
I wish none of this had happened.
每个人遇到难关都会这么想
So do all who live to see such times.
但是我们无法决定自己的命运
But that is not for them to decide.
我们要决定的是在一定的时间内怎么做
All we have to decide is what to do with the time that is given to us.
佛罗多，世上除了邪恶之外还有别的力量
There are other forces at work in this world, Frodo, besides the will of evil.
比尔博注定要找到魔戒
Bilbo was meant to find the Ring.
这样，你也注定要得到它
In which case, you also were meant to have it.
能这么想就好了
And that is an encouraging thought.
这个方向
It's that way.
- 他记起来了 - 没有
- He's remembered. - No.
但是这儿的空气没那么糟
But the air doesn't smell so foul down here.
梅里亚达克，要是迷了路，跟着鼻子走就对了
If in doubt, Meriadoc, always follow your nose.
我冒点险再弄亮一点
Let me risk a little more light.
看吧…
Behold…
这就是宏伟的矮人故乡摩瑞亚
the great realm and Dwarf-city of Dwarrowdelf.
这真是令人大开眼界
There's an eye opener, and no mistake.
金灵！
Gimli!
不！
No!
哦，不！
Oh, no.
不
No.
“巴林长眠于此
"Here lies Balin…
方丁之子…
son of Fundin…
摩瑞亚之王”
Lord of Moria."
他死了
He is dead, then.
果然和我担心的一样
It's as I feared.
我们快走吧，别在这儿逗留
We must move on. We cannot linger.
“他们攻下桥梁和第二大厅
"They have taken the bridge and the second hall.
我们闩住大门
We have barred the gates…
却阻挡不了他们
but cannot hold them for long.
大地在撼动
The ground shakes.
鼓声…
Drums…
地底深处传来鼓声
drums in the deep.
我们逃不出去
We cannot get out.
黑暗中有一个阴影
A Shadow moves in the dark.
我们逃不出去
We cannot get out.
他们来了”
They are coming."
你这个蠢小子！
Fool of a Took!
下次你自己也跳下去算了，免得我们被你的蠢害死
Throw yourself in next time, and rid us of your stupidity!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
半兽人
Orcs!
退后！跟着甘道夫！
Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
他们有一只食人妖
They have a cave-troll.
让她们来吧！
Let them come!
摩瑞亚有一个矮人还没死呢
There is one Dwarf yet in Moria who still draws breath.
我越来越厉害了
I think I'm getting the hang of this.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
亚拉冈！亚拉冈！
Aragorn! Aragorn!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
不
Oh, no!
他还活着
He's alive.
我没事，我没受伤
I'm all right. I'm not hurt.
你应该没命的
You should be dead.
那一剑连野猪都能刺穿
That spear would have skewered a wild boar.
小哈比人远比我们想像的属害
I think there's more to this Hobbit than meets the eye.
秘银
Mithril.
你真是叫人惊讶，巴金斯大爷
You are full of surprises, Master Baggins.
快到凯萨督姆桥
To the Bridge of Khazad-dum!
这边！
This way!
又来了什么怪物？
What is this new devilry?
炎魔
A Balrog.
远古的恶魔
A demon of the ancient world.
你们都不是她的对手
This foe is beyond any of you.
快跑！
Run!
快点！
Quickly!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
带领他们，亚拉冈
Lead them on, Aragorn.
桥就快到了
The bridge is near.
听我的话！快去吧，剑是无法对付炎魔的
Do as I say! Swords are no more use here.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
梅里！皮聘！
Merry! Pippin!
山姆
Sam!
谁也不能丢矮人
Nobody tosses a Dwarf.
别抓我胡子！
Not the beard!
稳着点
Steady.
站好！
Hold on!
稳住！
Hang on!
往前倾！
Lean forward!
稳着点
Steady.
快点
Come on!
快跳！
Now!
快过桥！
Over the bridge!
快过去！
Fly!
你不能过来！
You cannot pass!
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
我是圣火的仆人，高举着亚尔诺炽焰
I am a servant of the Secret Fire, wielder of the flame of Anor.
邪恶之火不会帮你，乌顿之火！
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udun!
滚回黑暗中吧
Go back to the Shadow.
你不能过来！
You shall not pass!
- 不行！不行！ - 甘道夫！
- No! No! - Gandalf!
傻孩子，你们快走吧！
Fly, you fools!
不行！
No!
亚拉冈！
Aragorn!
勒苟拉斯，把他们扶起来
Legolas, get them up.
让他们静一静吧！
Give them a moment, for pity's sake!
天一黑半兽人就会蜂拥而上
By nightfall, these hills will be swarming with Orcs.
我们一定要赶到罗斯洛立安
We must reach the woods of Lothlorien.
走吧，波罗莫、勒苟拉斯，金灵，把他们扶起来
Come, Boromir. Legolas. Gimli, get them up.
站起来，山姆
On your feet, Sam.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
佛罗多！
Frodo!
跟紧了，小哈比人
Stay close, young Hobbits!
听说这儿住了可怕的女巫
They say that a great sorceress lives in these woods.
她是一个精灵
An Elf-witch…
拥有强大的力量
of terrible power.
只要看她一眼…
All who look upon her…
就会被她蛊惑
fall under her spell.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
然后永远消失
And are never seen again.
你来到这里，带来毁灭的消息
Your coming to us is as the footsteps of doom.
你把强大的邪恶带来，魔戒持有者
You bring great evil here, Ring-bearer.
佛罗多大爷？
Mr. Frodo?
她可骗不了我这矮人
Well, here's one Dwarf she won't ensnare so easily.
我有老鹰的锐眼、孤狸的耳朵
I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox.
这矮子太聒噪，就算闭着眼睛也能射中他
The Dwarf breathes so loud, we could have shot him in the dark.
[精灵语] 欢迎勒苟拉斯，瑟兰督伊之子
Welcome Legolas, son of Thranduil.
[精灵语] 我们远征队永远感激你们
Our Fellowship stands in your debt.
[精灵语] 登丹人亚拉冈
Aragorn of the Dunedain…
我们都认得你
you are known to us.
传说中精灵不都是很有礼貌吗？
So much for the legendary courtesy of the Elves!
说我们都听得懂的话！
Speak words we can all understand!
我们从黑暗时期之后就未曾与矮人往来过
We have not had dealings with the Dwarves since the Dark Days.
你知道这矮人会怎么说吗？
And you know what this Dwarf says to that?
那很没有礼貌
That was not so courteous.
你带来了强大的邪恶力量
You bring great evil with you.
你们的旅程不能再继续
You can go no further.
甘道夫不可以白死
Gandalf's death was not in vain.
他也不会要你放弃希望
Nor would he have you give up hope.
佛罗多，你的负担很重
You carry a heavy burden, Frodo.
不要连哀悼也一起背负着
Don't carry the weight of the dead.
你们跟我来
You will follow me.
卡拉斯加拉顿
Caras Galadhon.
地球上精灵之乡的主城
The heart of Elvendom on earth.
精灵皇凯勒鹏与光之女王凯兰崔尔统治之地
Realm of the Lord Celeborn and of Galadriel, Lady of Light.
魔君知道你们已经来到此地
The enemy knows you have entered here.
你们保持隐密的希望已经破灭了
What hope you had in secrecy is now gone.
这儿只有八人，但是有九人从瑞文戴尔出发
Eight there are here, yet nine there were set out from Rivendell.
告拆我，甘道夫呢？
Tell me, where is Gandalf?
我想跟他说话
For I much desire to speak with him.
我从远方就看不到他了
I can no longer see him from afar.
灰袍巫师甘道夫没能越过这里的边界
Gandalf the Grey did not pass the borders of this land.
他堕入黑暗深渊
He has fallen into Shadow.
他被炎魔吞噬了
He was taken by both Shadow and flame.
是魔苟斯炎魔
A Balrog of Morgoth.
因为我们毫无必要的进入摩瑞亚网中
For we went needlessly into the net of Moria.
毫无必要不是甘道夫一生中会做的事
Needless were none of the deeds of Gandalf in life.
我们还无法知悉他的用意为何
We do not yet know his full purpose.
不要让凯萨督姆巨大的虚空占据你的心
Do not let the great emptiness of Khazad-dum fill your heart…
金灵，葛罗音之子
Gimli, son of Gloin.
这世界儿满了危险…
For the world has grown full of peril…
在每一个角落
and in all lands…
爱已经混杂了悲痛
love is now mingled with grief.
现在远征队怎么办？
What now becomes of this Fellowship?
没有甘道夫，希望就破灭了
Without Gandalf, hope is lost.
这趟旅程险象环生
The quest stands upon the edge of a knife.
你们只要一不小心就会失败
Stray but a little and it will fail…
世界末日也会来临
to the ruin of all.
只要图结一致就有一线希望
Yet hope remains while the Company is true.
你们的信心不能动摇，快去休息吧
Do not let your hearts be troubled. Go now and rest…
你们有太多的哀伤和疲惫
for you are weary with sorrow and much toil.
今晚你们要睡在…
Tonight, you will sleep…
欢迎，夏尔的佛罗多
Welcome, Frodo of the Shire…
只有你见过邪眼！
one who has seen the Eye!
他们在为甘道夫哀悼
A lament for Gandalf.
他们说些什么？
What do they say about him?
我不忍心告拆你
I have not the heart to tell you.
对我来说，伤口仍然太痛了
For me, the grief is still too near.
我敢说他们一定不会提起他的烟火
I bet they don't mention his fireworks.
他们应该写首诗歌
There should be a verse about them.
举世无匹烟火秀
The finest rockets ever seen
晶亮蓝绿成星辰
They burst in stars of blue and green
迅若闪电，灿如银雨
Or after thunder, silver showers
天女散花差可掇
Came falling like a rain of flowers
这完全无法形容其精彩程度之万一
Oh, that doesn't do them justice by a long road.
休息吧
Take some rest.
这里很安全
These borders are well-protected.
我在这里无法休息
I will find no rest here.
我听到她的声音
I heard her voice inside my head.
她提到我父舰和刚铎的灭亡
She spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor.
她说现在仍有一线希望
She said to me, "Even now there is hope left."
但是我却看不到
But I cannot see it.
我们长久以来都没有希望
It is long since we had any hope.
我父亲摊有高贵情操
My father is a noble man.
但是他无法统治刚铎
But his rule is failing…
人民也失去信心
and our people lose faith.
他希望我能成功，我也希望
He looks to me to make things right, and I would do it.
我想要重建刚铎的荣耀
I would see the glory of Gondor restored.
你见过吗，亚拉冈？
Have you ever seen it, Aragorn?
爱克西里昂的白塔
The White Tower of Ecthelion.
像珍珠和白银一般闪闪发亮
Glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver.
塔上的旗子随风飘扬
Its banners caught high in the morning breeze.
你有没有听过
Have you ever been called home…
银喇叭的召唤声？
by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
我很久以前见过
I have seen the White City…
这白色城市
long ago.
有一天，我们会一起去那儿
One day, our paths will lead us there.
到时候守卫将高喊
And the tower guard shall take up the call:
“刚铎之主回来了”
"The Lords of Gondor have returned."
请你看着镜子
Will you look into the mirror?
我会看到什么？
What will I see?
最聪明的智者也不知道
Even the wisest cannot tell.
因为镜子…
For the mirror…
能显现各种事情
shows many things.
过去的事情
Things that were…
现在的事情
things that are…
还有一些…
and some things…
尚未发生的事情
that have not yet come to pass.
我知道你看到什么
I know what it is you saw.
那也在我心里呈现
For it is also in my mind.
如果你失败就会发生这些事
It is what will come to pass if you should fail.
魔戒远征队已经开始四分五裂
The Fellowship is breaking. It is already begun.
他会试图抢走魔戒
He will try to take the Ring.
你知道我说的是谁
You know of whom I speak.
他们会一一被魔戒击垮
One by one, it will destroy them all.
你要的话…
If you ask it of me…
我就把至尊魔戒给称
I will give you the One Ring.
你毫无涤件的给我
You offer it to me freely?
我承认我很想要魔戒
I do not deny that my heart has greatly desired this.
我将成为魔戒之后
In place of a Dark Lord, you would have a queen…
并不黑暗，而是美丽，跟曙光一样耀眼！
not dark but beautiful, and terrible as the dawn!
跟海洋一样高深莫测！
Treacherous as the sea!
远比土地更加坚强！
Stronger than the foundations of the earth!
世人都将绝望地…
All shall love me…
热爱我
and despair.
我通过考验了
I pass the test. I will diminish…
我会退隐到西方
and go into the West…
- 继续当凯兰崔尔女王 - 我一个人无法摧毁它
- and remain Galadriel. - I cannot do this alone.
你是魔戒持有者，佛罗多，持有至尊魔戒
You are a Ring-bearer, Frodo. To bear a Ring of Power…
就必须孤单一个人
is to be alone.
这是钻石魔戒南雅
This is Nenya, the Ring of Adamant.
我就是这颗魔戒的持有者
And I am its keeper.
这是你的天命
This task was appointed to you.
如果你办不到…
And if you do not find a way…
也没有人可以
no one will.
我知道该怎么做了
Then I know what I must do.
只是…
It's just…
我感到害怕
I'm afraid to do it.
再渺小的人也能改变未来
Even the smallest person can change the course of the future.
你知道半兽人是怎么来的吗？
Do you know how the Orcs first came into being?
她们曾经是精灵
They were Elves once.
但是却被黑暗力量
Taken by the Dark Powers…
折磨到不成人形
tortured and mutilated.
她们是被扭曲的可怕生物
A ruined and terrible form of life.
现在却在我手中…
And now…
远到完美境界
perfected.
我的强兽人战士
My fighting Uruk-hai…
你的主人是谁？
whom do you serve?
萨鲁曼
Saruman!
猎杀他们，找不到绝不罢手
Hunt them down. Do not stop until they are found.
你们没有痛苦也没有恐惧
You do not know pain. You do not know fear.
你们只会杀人！
You will taste Man-flesh!
有一个半身人，携带着价值连城的东西
One of the halflings carries something of great value.
连人带物捉来见我
Bring them to me alive and unspoiled.
杀了其他人
Kill the others.
我们从未让外人穿戴上我们的衣裳
Never before have we clad strangers in the garb of our own people.
希望披风能保护你们不受邪眼侵扰
May these cloaks help shield you from unfriendly eyes.
兰巴斯
Lembas.
精灵的行路面包
Elvish waybread.
一小口就可以填饱一个成人
One small bite is enough to fill the stomach of a grown man.
你吃了多少？
How many did you eat?
四颗
Four.
每往南方前进一步，危险就增加一分
Every league you travel south, the danger will increase.
魔多的半兽人现在把守了安都因河岸
Mordor Orcs now hold the eastern shore of the Anduin.
西岸也不安全
Nor will you find safety on the western bank.
脸上有白掌印的怪异生物曾在我们的边界出没
Strange creatures bearing the White Hand have been seen on our borders.
半兽人很少在阳光下走动，但是最近却曾看过一些
Seldom do Orcs journey in the open under the sun, yet these have done so.
[精灵语] 你们被跟踪了
You are being tracked.
顺着河走，你们有机会提脱魔君，先到达拉洛斯瀑布
By river you have the chance of outrunning the enemy to the Falls of Rauros.
我给你的礼物，勒苟拉斯，是凯兰崔姆树精灵的弓
My gift for you, Legolas, is a bow of the Galadhrim.
配得上森林同胞的武艺
Worthy of the skill of our woodland kin.
这是诺多精灵的匕首
These are the daggers of the Noldorin.
曾经上过战场
They have already seen service in war.
不要恐惧，皮瑞格林图克
Do not fear, young Peregrin Took.
你会找到勇气
You will find your courage.
而你的，山姆卫斯詹吉
And for you, Samwise Gamgee…
是用希斯蓝制作的精灵绳索
Elven rope made of hithlain.
谢谢您，女王
Thank you, my lady.
您没有那些好看闪亮的匕首了吗？
Have you run out of those nice, shiny daggers?
矮人想从精灵这边要什么样的礼物？
And what gift would a dwarf ask of the Elves?
什么也不要
Nothing.
只求能再看一眼，凯兰崔姆女王的容颜
Except to look upon the lady of the Galadhrim one last time…
她的容颜比地底下所有的珠宝更灿烂
for she is more fair than all the jewels beneath the earth.
其实…
Actually…
有一项东西
There was one thing.
不，我在说傻话，这是不可能的
No, no, I couldn't. It's quite impossible.
很蠢的的间题
Stupid to ask.
我没有什么…
I have nothing greater to give…
会比你拥有的更珍贵
than the gift you already bear.
[精灵语] 她的爱
For her love,
我恐怕亚玟灿星的力量会减弱
I fear the grace of Arwen Evenstar will diminish.
[精灵语] 我会要她远离河岸
I would have her leave these shores,
跟她的族人在一起
and be with her people.
我会要她乘船到瓦林诺
I would have her take the ship to Valinor.
做选择的是她
That choice is yet before her.
你自己也有抉择要做，亚拉冈
You have your own choice to make, Aragorn.
克服你所有的祖先面对的障碍，从伊兰迪尔在位那时的开始
To rise above the height of all your fathers since the days of Elendil…
或者是跟你的家族一样堕入黑暗深渊
or to fall into darkness with all that is left of your kin.
[精灵语] 再会
Farewell.
[精灵语] 你还有很多事要做
There is much you have yet to do.
[精灵语] 我们不会再见了
We shall not meet again…
伊力萨王
Elessar.
再见了，佛罗多巴金斯
Farewell, Frodo Baggins.
我给你埃兰迪尔之光
I give you the light of Earendil…
我们最挚爱的星辰
our most beloved star.
愿它在所有光亮熄灭时
May it be a light for you in dark places…
在黑暗中为你照明
when all other lights go out.
这次离开让我再心痛不过
I have taken my worst wound at this parting…
那是我最后一次见到最美丽的容颜
having looked my last upon that which is fairest.
从此之后，对我来说除了她的礼物，没有什么是美的
Henceforth I will call nothing fair unless it be her gift to me.
她的礼物是什么？
What was her gift?
我跟她要一根她的金发
I asked her for one hair from her golden head.
她给了我三根
She gave me three.
咕鲁，他从摩瑞亚开始就一直跟踪我们
Gollum. He has tracked us since Moria.
我还希望能在河上提脱他
I had hoped we would lose him on the river.
但是他太熟知水性
But he's too clever a waterman.
如果他告知魔君我们现在的方位
And if he alerts the enemy to our whereabouts…
我们渡河就更危险了
it will make the crossing even more dangerous.
吃点东西，佛罗多大斧
Have some food, Mr. Frodo.
- 不了，山姆 - 你整天都没吃东西
- No, Sam. - You haven't eaten anything all day.
也睡不着，不要以为我没有注意到
You're not sleeping, neither. Don't think I haven't noticed.
- 佛罗多大爷… - 我很好
- Mr. Frodo… - I'm all right.
但是你不好
But you're not.
我是来帮助你的
I'm here to help you.
我跟甘道夫保证过我会帮助你
I promised Gandalf that I would.
你帮不上忙的，山姆
You can't help me, Sam.
这次帮不上
Not this time.
睡一下吧
Get some sleep.
米那斯提力斯比较安全
Minas Tirith is the safer road.
你知道的，那里我们可以重整力量
You know that. From there we can regroup.
更利于我们出发到达魔多
Strike out for Mordor from a place of strength.
刚铎对我们而言没有什么有利之处
There is no strength in Gondor that can avail us.
你很轻易就信任精灵
You were quick enough to trust the Elves.
你对人类自己就没有信心吗？
Have you so little faith in your own people?
对，我们有弱点，我们有缺陷
Yes, there is weakness. There is frailty.
但是人类也有勇气与荣誊感
But there is courage also, and honor to be found in Men.
但是你不肯承认
But you will not see that.
你在恐惧！
You are afraid!
你一生都藏在阴影之中
All your life, you have hidden in the shadows.
恐惧你的来处，你的身分
Scared of who you are, of what you are.
我不会让魔戒靠近你的城市
I will not lead the Ring within a hundred leagues of your city.
佛罗多
Frodo.
亚苟那斯巨像
The Argonath.
我一直都想仰望过往的王者
Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old.
我的祖先
My kin.
天一黑就过湖
We cross the lake at nightfall.
把船藏好再用走的
Hide the boats and continue on foot.
- 从北边进入魔多 - 是吗？
- We approach Mordor from the North. - Oh, yes?
只要通过爱明莫尔就行了？
Just a simple matter of finding our way through Emyn Muil…
那是充满尖石的迷宫
an impassable labyrinth of razor-sharp rocks.
然后呢，就更精采了
And after that, it gets even better.
那儿有一望无际的臭沼泽地
Festering, stinking marshland as far as the eye can see.
我们要走这条路
That is our road.
我建议你休息吧，养精蓄锐
I suggest you take some rest and recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
养精蓄锐个头…
Recover my…
- 我们最好马上启程 - 不行
- We should leave now. - No.
半兽人在巡逻东岸，一定要等到天黑再出发
Orcs patrol the eastern shore. We must wait for cover of darkness.
我担心的不是东岸
It is not the eastern shore that worries me.
我心中一直有一个阴影，一个逐渐壮大的威胁
A shadow and a threat has been growing in my mind.
有什么正在接近，我感觉得到
Something draws near. I can feel it.
矮人族才不必养精蓄锐，别理他，小哈比人
Recover strength? Pay no heed to that, young Hobbit.
佛罗多呢？
Where's Frodo?
我们都不该一个人乱跑
None of us should wander alone.
尤其是你
You, least of all.
你的责任重大
So much depends on you.
佛罗多？
Frodo?
我知道你想一个人静静
I know why you seek solitude.
我天天看着你受苦
You suffer. I see it day by day.
你确定你不是白白受苦？
You sure you do not suffer needlessly?
有其他的路，佛罗多
There are other ways, Frodo.
- 我们可以走其他的路 - 我知道你想说什么
- Other paths that we might take. - I know what you would say.
好像很有道理，但我得到警告
It would seem like wisdom but for the warning in my heart.
警告？什么警告？
Warning? Against what?
我们都很害怕，佛罗多
We're all afraid, Frodo.
但如果让恐惧摧毁一切希望
But to let that fear drive us, to destroy what hope we have…
- 未免太荒谬了吧？ - 没有别的路可走
- don't you see that is madness? - There is no other way.
我需要捍卫人民的力量！
I ask only for the strength to defend my people!
- 把魔戒借我 - 不行
- If you would but lend me the Ring. - No.
- 你为何退缩？我不是强盗 - 你失去理智了
- Why do you recoil? I am no thief. - You are not yourself.
你以为你能成功吗？
What chance do you think you have?
他们会找到你，把魔戒抢走
They will find you. They will take the Ring.
让你求生不能、求死不得！
And you will beg for death before the end!
你这傻子！
You fool!
你只是靠运气得到它，它应该是我的，给我吧！
It is not yours, save by unhappy chance! It could have been mine.
它应该是我的！给我！
It should be mine! Give it to me!
- 快给我！ - 不！
- Give it to me! - No!
- 给我！ - 不！
- Give it to me! - No.
我知道了
I see your mind.
你会把魔戒给索伦！
You will take the Ring to Sauron!
你会背叛我们！
You will betray us!
你会害我们跟你一起死！
You'll go to your death, and the death of us all!
我诅咒你和所有的半身人！
Curse you! Curse you and all the halflings!
佛罗多？
Frodo?
佛罗多
Frodo.
我做了什么？
What have I done?
求求你，佛罗多
Please, Frodo.
佛罗多，对不起！
Frodo, I'm sorry!
佛罗多？
Frodo?
- 它盘惑了波罗莫 - 魔戒呢？
- It has taken Boromir. - Where is the Ring?
别过来！
Stay away!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
- 我发誓要保护你 - 你能保证不害我吗？
- I swore to protect you. - Can you protect me from yourself?
你会摧毁它吗？
Would you destroy it?
亚拉冈
Aragorn.
伊力萨王
Elessar.
我愿意跟随你到最后
I would have gone with you to the end.
跟随你到魔多烈焰
Into the very fires of Mordor.
我知道
I know.
好好照顾他们，尤其是山姆，他不会了解
Look after the others. Especially Sam. He will not understand.
去吧，佛罗多！
Go, Frodo!
快跑
Run!
快跑呀！
佛罗多大爷！
Mr. Frodo!
去找半身人！
Find the halfling!
伊兰迪尔！
Elendil!
亚拉冈，快走！
Aragorn, go!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
快躲过来！
Hide here. Quick!
快点！
Come on!
他在干嘛？
What's he doing?
他要离开了
He's leaving.
- 不！ - 皮聘！
- No! - Pippin!
快跑吧，佛罗多！
Run, Frodo. Go on!
- 喂！ - 在这儿！
- Hey! Hey, you! - Over here!
- 这里啦！ - 这边！
- Over here! - This way!
- 成功了！ - 我知道啦！快跑！
- It's working! - I know it's working! Run!
- 刚铎的号角 - 波罗莫
- The horn of Gondor. - Boromir.
快跑！
Run!
不
No.
- 他们把小的抓走了 - 别动
- They took the little ones. - Hold still.
佛罗多呢？佛罗多在哪里？
Frodo. Where is Frodo?
我让他走了
I let Frodo go.
你做到我做不到的事
Then you did what I could not.
我想要抢走魔戒
I tried to take the Ring from him.
- 现在谁也抢不走魔戒了 - 原谅我
- The Ring is beyond our reach now. - Forgive me.
我没想到
I did not see it.
- 我让大家失望了 - 不，波罗莫
- I have failed you all. - No, Boromir.
你英勇的作战
You fought bravely.
你维护了你的尊严
You have kept your honor.
算了
Leave it.
一切都结束了
It is over.
人类世界将灭亡，黑暗将笼罩大地
The world of Men will fall. And all will come to darkness…
我的城市将遭毁灭
and my city to ruin.
我不知道我有多大的力量
I do not know what strength is in my blood…
但我发誓绝不会让白城沦陷
but I swear to you, I will not let the White City fall…
也不会让我们的人民失败
nor our people fail.
我们的人民
Our people.
我愿跟随你，兄弟
I would have followed you, my brother.
我的领袖
My captain.
我的国王
My king.
安息吧
Be at peace…
刚铎之子
son of Gondor.
他们会盼望他回到白色要塞
They will look for his coming from the White Tower.
但是他回不去了
But he will not return.
佛罗多！
Frodo!
我真希望魔戒没在我手中
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
真希望这一切都没发生
I wish none of this had happened.
每个人遇到难关都会这么想
So do all who live to see such times…
但我们无法决定自己的命运
but that is not for them to decide.
你只能在
All you have to decide…
一定的时间内决定如何去做
is what to do with the time that is given to you.
不，佛罗多！
Frodo, no!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
- 佛罗多大爷！ - 不，山姆
- Mr. Frodo! - No, Sam.
回去吧，山姆！
Go back, Sam!
- 我要一个人去魔多 - 没问题
- I'm going to Mordor alone. - Of course you are.
但我要跟你一起去！
And I'm coming with you!
你不会游泳！
You can't swim!
山姆！
Sam!
我许下一个承诺，佛罗多大爷
I made a promise, Mr. Frodo.
这个承诺是：“千万别离开他，山姆卫斯詹吉”
A promise: "Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."
我绝不离开你
And I don't mean to.
绝对不会
I don't mean to.
山姆
Sam.
来吧
Come on.
快！佛果多和山姆到东岸了
Hurry! Frodo and Sam have reached the eastern shore.
- 你不打算跟去 - 我们帮不了佛罗多了
- You mean not to follow them. - Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
那我们一切的努力都白费了，远征队也彻底失败
Then it has all been in vain. The Fellowship has failed.
我们的努力不会白费
Not if we hold true to each other.
我们不能丢下梅里和皮聘让他们受苦
We will not abandon Merry and Pippin to torment and death.
只要我们还有力气，不用的都留下来
Not while we have strength left. Leave all that can be spared behind.
尽量减轻负担
We travel light.
我们去猎杀半兽人吧
Let us hunt some Orc.
好耶！
Yes!
魔多
Mordor.
希望其他人走的路比较安全
I hope the others find a safer road.
神行客会照顾他们的
Strider will look after them.
我想我们不会再见到他们了
I don't suppose we'll ever see them again.
佛罗多大爷，我们也许还会再见
We may yet, Mr. Frodo.
也许会
We may.
山姆
Sam…
我很高兴有你陪着我
I'm glad you are with me.